<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true conduct of persons of quality translated out of French.</title>
            <title>Véritable politique des personnes de qualité. English</title>
            <author>Rémond des Cours, Nicolas, d. 1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R958A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13024705</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13024705</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96673</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96673)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 398:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true conduct of persons of quality translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>Véritable politique des personnes de qualité. English</title>
                  <author>Rémond des Cours, Nicolas, d. 1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 191, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Véritable politique des personnes de qualité.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Nicolas Rémond des Cours. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Table of contents: [8] p. at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Courtesy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:1"/>
            <p>THE TRUE CONDUCT OF Perſons OF QUALITY.</p>
            <p>TRANSLATED OUT OF <hi>FRENCH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> MDCXCIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:2"/>
            <head>The TRANSLATOR'S PREFACE TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THIS Little Tract is bent <hi>Honeſtly</hi> to inform in a few Words the <hi>Upper Rank</hi> of Men with ſuch Rules of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Morality, as may be therefore more ſeaſonable, becauſe they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd to Generous Minds, which may be taken by Hints, when neither their Leiſure, nor their Inclination will permit 'em to be approach'd by elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Harangues of a nauſeous length. The Tranſlator has endeavour'd that the Author might breath the Strength of his own Thought, and live tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in our Clime; but his chief Aim is, that theſe Maxims may conduce to
<pb facs="tcp:96673:3"/>the carrying up of Virtue to a Noble Pitch, and that he may not lie under the Reproach of wanting the Will to do good to thoſe, whom he fancies very often to ſtand in need of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Suggeſtions; which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to your View in this Order. Becauſe <hi>an Honeſt Man</hi> is not ſo well as abandon'd, but upbraided for being ſteadily ſo: In the <hi>Firſt Section</hi> he is ſet forth as a ſuitable Preliminary to uſher in the other Heads. In the <hi>Second,</hi> the <hi>Duty of Honoring Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> is <hi>Countenanc'd</hi> and <hi>encourag'd.</hi> In the <hi>Third,</hi> the <hi>Importance of Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is <hi>Recommended,</hi> as the moſt <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent</hi> Act of <hi>Indulgent Parents,</hi> the moſt univerſally neceſſary to <hi>faſhion Great Men,</hi> and to <hi>Relieve</hi> the <hi>Unhappy.</hi> The 4th. ſpecifies the Particulars of the <hi>Education,</hi> and deſcribes to you, <hi>What a young Gentleman is to Learn.</hi> The <hi>Fifth</hi> draws him a Line from whence he is to make no <hi>Excurſions,</hi> by <hi>ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> him, <hi>what ought to be the Scope of his Studies.</hi> Under the <hi>Sixth Head</hi> he is confin'd <hi>to make a Right Uſe</hi> of his
<pb facs="tcp:96673:3"/>Knowledge, but this cannot be done, as the <hi>Seventh</hi> acquaints him, without <hi>doing what becomes him for his Relations.</hi> The <hi>Eighth,</hi> adviſeth you <hi>to be ſubject to the Laws of the Country;</hi> and not to arraign 'em, if there ſhould be a Male-Adminiſtration. The <hi>Ninth</hi> tears up all Rebellion by the Roots, by ſhewing, that the Duty of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is the ſupreme Law. The <hi>Tenth</hi> is a pointed Satyr <hi>againſt them who dare cenſure the Government.</hi> The <hi>Eleventh</hi> laſhes thoſe who make Inroads upon our Quiet, as all <hi>Fomenters of Plots and Diſturbances do.</hi> The <hi>Twelfth chalks us out the true way to gain Eſteem.</hi> In the <hi>Thirteenth,</hi> the Advantages of High Birth, and Reputation are ſet forth. In the <hi>Fourteenth,</hi> that he may not be fluctuating what he ſhall chuſe, nor do it raſhly, Rules are ſet him for the <hi>Choice of a Station in the World.</hi> And becauſe a Man of Quality may not ſo readily part with Eaſe, the <hi>Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth</hi> gives him Reaſons why he ſhould be <hi>vigilant, intent, and laborious.</hi> The <hi>Sixteenth</hi> puts him upon deſigning his
<pb facs="tcp:96673:4"/>Actions ſo juſtly, that he may be ſure not to miſcarry in the <hi>Firſt Undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> The <hi>Seventeenth</hi> puts him into the Track, how he may with moſt Eaſe form an Intereſt in the <hi>Eſteem of Princes and Great Men.</hi> The <hi>Eighteenth,</hi> from a due Picture of the Miſery of thoſe who are depriv'd of Friends, takes occaſion to exalt the <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of thoſe who find 'em. The <hi>Nineteenth</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally then leads a Man of Quality nicely to diſtinguiſh what ſort of <hi>Friends</hi> they are, whom he will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to <hi>preſide</hi> in his <hi>Soul.</hi> In the <hi>Twentieth, our Time,</hi> which ſo <hi>unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably ſteals</hi> away, is <hi>arreſted</hi> by the <hi>Obſervations</hi> of this <hi>Author;</hi> and as the Fate of <hi>miſemploying</hi> it is ſet forth, a <hi>Model</hi> whereby to improve it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd. The <hi>Twenty firſt</hi> taxeth the <hi>Vanity</hi> of <hi>Tatlers,</hi> and <hi>labours</hi> to fill your <hi>Imagination</hi> with the <hi>Conveniency</hi> of <hi>Silence.</hi> The <hi>Twenty ſecond</hi> is ſo far from allowing any <hi>Honor</hi> to be acquir'd by <hi>Duels,</hi> that he ſhews that all that are intereſted in 'em are diſobedient to an Exceſs both againſt <hi>God</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:96673:4"/>
               <hi>King.</hi> The <hi>Twenty third</hi> ſhews, that <hi>Miniſters of State</hi> are neither <hi>ſervilely</hi> to be apply'd to, nor is it reaſonable to expect to be entitled to their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> by <hi>ſlighting</hi> of 'em. The <hi>Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fourth</hi> Maxim <hi>circumſcribes</hi> your <hi>Pleaſures</hi> within a due Compaſs. The <hi>Twenty fifth</hi> acquaints you what <hi>auk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Conduct</hi> Men are under the Power of, for want of <hi>throughly ſtudying</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. The <hi>Twenty ſixth</hi> diſcovers how <hi>uſeful</hi> 'tis to hold Converſation with Men eminent for Wiſdom, and of <hi>great Abilities.</hi> The <hi>Twenty ſeventh</hi> repreſents, what <hi>Variety</hi> of <hi>Friends</hi> is neceſſary to abate the Ruggedneſs of Life. The <hi>Twenty eighth</hi> deſcribes what <hi>Turn</hi> your <hi>Mind</hi> muſt have if you will <hi>embark</hi> in <hi>Great Deſigns.</hi> Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion makes every thing look ſo rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt, ſo ſtrain'd, and unnatural, that the <hi>Twenty ninth</hi> hiſſes it off the Stage. The <hi>Thirtieth</hi> puts a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> upon <hi>diving</hi> into what will <hi>take</hi> with the Age. The <hi>Thirty firſt</hi> inſtructs him, that he may find <hi>uſeful Pleaſantry</hi> to entertain himſelf with when he is <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:5"/>The <hi>Thirty ſecond</hi> blames thoſe who will run down an <hi>Undertaking,</hi> which is not <hi>anſwer'd</hi> with a <hi>proſperous Event.</hi> The <hi>Thirty third</hi> marks the Limits how far the <hi>Compliance</hi> with a <hi>Friend</hi> is <hi>warrantable.</hi> Tho the <hi>Thirty fourth</hi> doth not permit a Perſon of <hi>Quality deſignedly</hi> to turn <hi>Droll,</hi> yet it <hi>commends</hi> him for <hi>ſprinkling</hi> ſome <hi>Gaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in his <hi>Humour.</hi> The <hi>Thirty fifth</hi> ſhews that by a <hi>Neglect</hi> in a <hi>ſlight</hi> Matter, a <hi>whole Hopeful Deſign</hi> may be loſt. The <hi>Thirty ſixth</hi> deſcribes the ways of becoming a <hi>Darling throughly ſettled,</hi> and to be <hi>Riveted</hi> in the <hi>Favour</hi> of <hi>Great Men.</hi> The <hi>Thirty ſeventh pares</hi> off the <hi>Folly</hi> of <hi>Superfluity,</hi> but gives <hi>Neatneſs</hi> its due Character. The <hi>Thirty eighth</hi> inſinuates what <hi>Length</hi> a Man's <hi>Diligence</hi> muſt <hi>reach</hi> who will <hi>create</hi> to <hi>himſelf no Enemies.</hi> The <hi>Thirty ninth</hi> is an <hi>Exhortation</hi> not to be <hi>diſpirited</hi> under the <hi>Cruſhings</hi> of the <hi>ſtrongeſt ſide.</hi> The <hi>Fortieth</hi> neither gives us leave to be the <hi>Tools</hi> of other Mens <hi>Pride,</hi> nor to <hi>propagate</hi> any of our <hi>own.</hi> The <hi>Forty firſt</hi> requires
<pb facs="tcp:96673:5"/>ſuch who would be <hi>Caſt-keepers</hi> for the <hi>Publick,</hi> to give Proofs before-hand, with what Management they can <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern</hi> their own Expences. The <hi>Forty ſecond</hi> introduceth Men of Quality to an Acquaintance inconſiderable for Number, but ſuch as have a great deal of intrinſick Value. The <hi>Forty third ſeverely</hi> checks all Satyrical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections, and <hi>Sharp Raillery.</hi> The <hi>Forty fourth</hi> gives <hi>Sincerity</hi> that Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick to which 'tis juſtly entitl'd. In the <hi>Forty fifth</hi> the Author <hi>modeſtly</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claims againſt ſuch as having once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up a <hi>Feud</hi> are averſe to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil'd, and in ſome meaſure tunes the <hi>jarring</hi> of Mens <hi>Minds;</hi> and when their <hi>Pulſe</hi> beats <hi>even,</hi> then he looks upon it as a proper occaſion in the <hi>Forty ſixth,</hi> to ſhew that it is beneath the <hi>Dignity</hi> of a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Honor</hi> to be Fickle. The <hi>Forty ſeventh ſcourges</hi> all who are of a <hi>Cowardly</hi> and <hi>Faint-hearted Character.</hi> The <hi>Forty eighth</hi> diſcovers that Gratitude is not only a Good manner'd Virtue, but that thoſe who only conſult Intereſt are no <hi>Loſers</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:6"/>by <hi>that Treaſure.</hi> The <hi>Forty ninth</hi> gives ſo <hi>mild</hi> an <hi>Admonition,</hi> that a Diſputer of the <hi>keeneſt Mettle</hi> is thereby re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd in the <hi>Vehemence</hi> of his <hi>Carier.</hi> The <hi>Fiftieth</hi> recommends <hi>Regular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Life,</hi> and ſhews where 'tis <hi>inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> it ſhould be <hi>All</hi> of <hi>a piece.</hi> The <hi>Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty firſt</hi> plainly makes it appear, that the quickeſt Underſtanding cannot pronounce <hi>judiciouſly</hi> of a Man, unleſs they have ſeen him under the <hi>Gawdy Temptations</hi> of a <hi>Full Fortune,</hi> or the <hi>preſſing Neceſſities</hi> of a <hi>Scanty.</hi> The <hi>Fifty ſecond</hi> prefers that Man of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as deſerving the moſt ample Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations who can ſteer <hi>evenly</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>both,</hi> with an <hi>eaſie Indifference.</hi> The <hi>Fifty third</hi> ſets down the <hi>Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience</hi> there is in reaching forth <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Letters</hi> to every one who has the Confidence to requeſt 'em; and if <hi>that</hi> renders <hi>Men of Honor</hi> liable to be put upon, <hi>ſigning</hi> 'em with <hi>Blanks,</hi> carries 'em into <hi>double Danger.</hi> The <hi>Fifty fourth ſtints Curioſity,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers where its true <hi>Uſe</hi> is to be fix'd. The <hi>Fifty fifth</hi> puts an <hi>Incapacity</hi> upon
<pb facs="tcp:96673:6"/>
               <hi>two</hi> Sorts of People for <hi>Companions</hi> which are <hi>Deboſhees,</hi> and <hi>Cowards.</hi> In the <hi>Fifty ſixth</hi> all <hi>Tricking</hi> is <hi>arraign'd,</hi> beſides what is <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>countermine</hi> the <hi>Trickers.</hi> In the <hi>Fifty ſeventh</hi> you are told what a <hi>fatal Stroke</hi> the <hi>Death</hi> of a Friend is; and which is the beſt way to <hi>heal</hi> the <hi>Wound</hi> it makes. The <hi>Fifty eighth</hi> bids a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> ſeriouſly conſider what <hi>tickliſh Ground</hi> he ſtands on at <hi>Court,</hi> and how many are at work to <hi>trip</hi> up his <hi>Heels.</hi> The <hi>Fifty ninth</hi> gives us to underſtand, what a <hi>Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cative to Laughter</hi> the <hi>Motly Figure</hi> of a <hi>Grey-headed Gallant</hi> is. The <hi>Sixtieth</hi> ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifies what Counſels a Man of Quality is not only to <hi>excuſe,</hi> but to <hi>encourage,</hi> and what he is oblig'd in Honor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and to puniſh the Broacher. The Author in the <hi>Sixty firſt</hi> ſeems to be ſenſible what a number of <hi>untraceable</hi> Spirits a Man <hi>advanc'd</hi> to a <hi>high Statior,</hi> has to <hi>conjure down;</hi> and therefore he proportions ſuitable Qualifications, either to carry on the <hi>Attack</hi> agaiſnt 'em, or at leaſt reſolutely to ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Defenſive. Becauſe <hi>Froth</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb facs="tcp:96673:7"/>ways uppermoſt, the <hi>Sixty ſecond Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> adviſeth never to anſwer when you are in a <hi>Ferment;</hi> for when the Matter is of <hi>Moment,</hi> 'tis good to ſtay for a becalm'd Temper. The <hi>Sixty third</hi> clears that Truth, that <hi>he</hi> who has already a <hi>profligate Bias,</hi> ought to have no <hi>Patron</hi> by the Authority of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to <hi>countenance</hi> him <hi>farther</hi> to out-run his Duty. The <hi>Sixty fourth</hi> teaches a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> thus to <hi>deal</hi> with the <hi>Ungrateful,</hi> not to be ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vindictive, but by the wonted <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> of <hi>ſoft Treatment,</hi> to ſhame 'em into a Senſe of their own Omiſſion. In the <hi>Sixty fifth</hi> you are given to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that becauſe there are no petty Conſequences which attend <hi>Great Undertakings,</hi> 'tis <hi>ſtark Nonſence</hi> to bring an <hi>ordinary Application</hi> to 'em. The <hi>Sixty ſixth</hi> leads a <hi>Perſon of Quality</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Belief how <hi>neceſſary</hi> Secreſie is to him, that it is a <hi>mighty falſe ſtep</hi> to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim</hi> his Steerage to the World, and ſo <hi>arm</hi> his <hi>Adverſary</hi> to <hi>undo</hi> him, and that nothing can diſpenſe with his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulging of a Secret, but where the
<pb facs="tcp:96673:7"/>concealing of it would <hi>affront</hi> his <hi>God, betray</hi> his <hi>King,</hi> and naturally tend to the Ruine of his Country. In the <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeventh</hi> the Author makes it a proof of a <hi>Miſhapen Mind,</hi> that it muſt either be <hi>fluſh'd with extravagant</hi> Hopes of Things that are out of its reach to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine upon; or elſe with as irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar a Motion to be immediately <hi>toſs'd</hi> into the <hi>Depths</hi> of <hi>ſcandalous Deſpair.</hi> The 68th. <hi>Section</hi> endeavours to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince a <hi>Great Man,</hi> that it is his Duty to deter Vice, and to take <hi>Virtues Part,</hi> let the <hi>Attempt coſt</hi> what it will. The 69th. makes it appear how <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly Trivial</hi> that <hi>Humour</hi> is, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually hovering about Buſineſs, and entering upon none; <hi>ſpinning</hi> out <hi>Time</hi> ſo long till the <hi>Lucky Minute</hi> for execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Deſign is ſlip'd by, and can by no Art be <hi>brib'd</hi> to return. The 70th. give <hi>ſecure Directions</hi> to moderate that <hi>over-boiling Heat</hi> by which Men are <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitated</hi> to paſs <hi>fatal Sentences</hi> on themſelves by making <hi>a wrong Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> both on <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Things.</hi> The 71ſt. Head decyphers both how <hi>unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:8"/>and impolitick that Conduct is, where two have been <hi>Partners</hi> in an <hi>Undertaking</hi> that has <hi>ſucceeded,</hi> for one to <hi>uſurp</hi> all the <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and to <hi>rob</hi> the other of his <hi>Share.</hi> The 72d. <hi>marks</hi> out the <hi>Road</hi> a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> muſt purſue, when he is (<hi>urpriz'd</hi> by a <hi>ſudden Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent which is juſt upon the Verge</hi> of <hi>breaking</hi> all his <hi>Meaſures.</hi> The 73d. <hi>Section</hi> is a little Medley of <hi>Moral</hi> Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, about Good Turns, Rewards, and the <hi>wiſe Diſpoſal</hi> of <hi>Employments.</hi> The 74th. derives down to us the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what a <hi>Power</hi> there is in ſome Mens <hi>Method</hi> of <hi>obliging,</hi> their Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>flows</hi> ſo <hi>eaſily,</hi> that it <hi>inſinuates</hi> it ſelf with <hi>Variety</hi> of <hi>Charms</hi> into the <hi>Soul</hi> of the <hi>oblig'd;</hi> 'tis here you learn the <hi>Knack</hi> how ſome <hi>Men</hi> of <hi>Quality</hi> can lend away Petitioners <hi>ſatisfi'd</hi> at the ſame time they are <hi>refus'd.</hi> The 75th. points out to you both the Advantages that a Man in <hi>Solitude</hi> has to diſcover <hi>Truth,</hi> and the Comforts which finiſh the Repoſe of his Mind in that <hi>Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing State,</hi> but yet diſcovers that all are not to be of this <hi>Bookiſh Flegmatick
<pb facs="tcp:96673:8"/>Form,</hi> this <hi>Machine</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> can never be <hi>turn'd</hi> but by <hi>Wheels</hi> that <hi>move</hi> with mone <hi>Vigour;</hi> and therefore as the Shoulders of Men of Quality are loaded with the <hi>Weight</hi> of publick Affairs, they deſerve at leaſt <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> to help 'em to ſupport it. The 76th. unveils to us what noble Thoughts may be <hi>extracted</hi> from a <hi>quick Inſpection</hi> into the <hi>Creatures</hi> we daily converſe with. The 77th. draws Baniſhment in ſuch fair Colours, that a <hi>State-Officer diſgracd</hi> may fetch <hi>Armour</hi> eno' from this little Magazine to defend him from any <hi>harſh Reſentment</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Change.</hi> The 78th. ſets forth this Conſolation, that if a <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>Quality keeps up</hi> but thoſe three Springs of <hi>Innocence, Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> and Reſolution in his Frame, he can never have one <hi>uneven</hi> Motion in a Priſon. In the 79th. the Author bids you ſtep off the Stage of a tumultuous World, and to make a <hi>Chriſtian-like</hi> Preparation for the Climes of Bliſs, puts you upon this ſingle Duty, to give Wings to your Devotion, and to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th ſuch a reſin'd Love of your
<pb facs="tcp:96673:9"/>deareſt Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as may exert it ſelf in a ſuitable Imitation of his bright Example. And now to wind up all, this kind Hand that has led you rhro' all the Mazes of a tedious Life, would not forbear accompanying you to the laſt Apartment, the Chambers of (what has been call'd the King of Terrours, and Griſly) Death. But with the <hi>trueſt Stamp</hi> of <hi>Friendſhip</hi> tells you, you may make it as deſirable as you pleaſe; and tho there may be a little Violence at the firſt ſeparation of two ſo nearly ally'd as the <hi>Soul,</hi> and the <hi>Body,</hi> yet upon an <hi>antecedent pious Proviſion,</hi> the <hi>Reunion</hi> of thoſe <hi>dear Companions</hi> will be attended with ſuch <hi>Extaſies</hi> of <hi>Joy,</hi> that no Man <hi>living</hi> need ſtand ſhivering on the Brink of Eternity, at the Minute he is to launch, but venture on the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment with a <hi>grave</hi> and becoming Chearfulneſs. I have no more to add, but my Hearty Prayers, that theſe <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Moral Notices,</hi> tho ſhort, may convey ſome ſeaſonable Information to thoſe Minds that we cannot come at to cultivate another way, and then my <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> will be equal to their <hi>Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96673:9"/>
            <head>The True CONDUCT OF PERSONS of QUALITY.</head>
            <p>THO Perſons of a High Rank have commonly bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Parts, and a quicker In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight into things than others, yet they ſometimes ſlide into thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes which ſacrifice their Fortune and Reputation in the World. 'Tis ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to diſcover from what Fountain the unlucky Occurrences in their Lives flow, 'tis only that in their Steerage moſt of 'em ſet themſelves no Rule, but often act as Humour, Freak, or the Extravagance of a Paſſion leads 'em; yet it is chiefly for the ſake of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96673:10"/>Perſons of good Extraction that Rules of Management are neceſſary, becauſe their Affairs are of moment, their Employments conſiderable, their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts nice, and difficult to conduct. Beſides they have uſually more ſecret or declared Enemies, who with criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Inſpection comment upon all they do, and are intent to get into a poor eſteem by the blaſting of others Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. All this ſhews the neceſſity they are under not to act but by the Rules of Prudence and true Conduct; and this alſo has prevailed with me to lay down here the Maxims which it is requiſite for them to purſue, in order to recommend their Wiſdom, and maintain their Character honorably in the World. There is not one of theſe Maxims which I do not believe to be as profitable in the Practice, as it is uſeful in the Speculation; yet I do not pretend that they are to be blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followed without due exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. I only propound that which appears to me the moſt reaſonable,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96673:10"/>and the moſt ſafe, with all the Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which an honeſt Man ought to uſe; who in writing does not ſolely aim at the Diſcovery of his Wit and Skill, but who would nakedly impart the Obſervations he has made, to thoſe who for want of Reflection, or Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, are not ſufficiently inſtructed in many Occurrences of Life, where it is of the higheſt Importance they ſhould be informed. To conclude, I have endeavoured to ſhew in, this Tract, how advantageous the Practice of true Wiſdom is, if it be conſidered only for its Influence on Civil Life, yet I have no deſign to inſinuate thereby, that Men ſhould level their Cares only to acquire or preſerve worldly Afflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; I have remarked on the contrary, that we ought to terminate our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in an End infinitely more noble, and to make this alone the Spur to puſh all our Actions, to render our ſelves accompliſhed in the Eyes of God, by an Obedience that is invigorated with Love, and grateful Acknowledgment.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96673:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> An Honeſt Man.</head>
               <p>TO be a Man of this Character exceeds all other Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeeing that it contains the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Virtues which we muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make uſe of in the proſecution of our Duty, and is at the ſame time the Foundation of true Merit, and the ground-Work of ſubſtantial Happineſs. Now as this excellent Accompliſhment purchaſeth for us eternal Glory, ſo it naturally conduceth to make us live re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putably, and to promote our Quiet in this lower World: For a perſon of ſingular Probity, is the Point where all wiſe and underſtanding Men cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Eſteem, and his Deſert opens his way to Employments of the firſt Rate; beſides, as he is exempt from all irregular Paſſion, he enjoys that happy Tranquillity which reigns in unſpotted Souls, and never finds the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96673:11"/>Peace of his Mind ruffled by the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Accidents which affect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, becauſe being always ſubmiſſive to the Decrees of Providence, his Conſolation is lodged in his own Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; and as nothing is able to raviſh from him that precious Treaſure which is included in himſelf, ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing has power enough to render him unhappy.</p>
               <p>This is not the Caſe of them who build their Happineſs upon Health, Beauty, Riches, Dignities, and ſuch other Largeſſes, as they have received from prodigal Nature, or blind For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; for all theſe are often a Prey to a thouſand unforeſeen Caſualties, or by the ſudden ſlipping out of their Hands, proclaim themſelves a-kin to all other human Affairs; and then are they ſo much the more miſerable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do not find within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves any ſuitable Conſolation ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, wherewith to compenſate the Loſs of thoſe fleeting Poſſeſſions which they were ſo paſſionately ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96673:12"/>of Nothing then is of more Advantage than to labour to become an Honeſt Man: To be ſo indeed, it is neceſſary to have a ſprightly and clear Faith, or in other Words, to be ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced of all the Truths of Chriſtianity, to follow its Rules exactly, and to have an extreme Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all Libertiniſm and Impiety. Our Religion carries along withit ſuch manifeſt Marks of the Divinity of its Original, it is ſo Amiable and ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the incredulous who dare to contemn it, are altogether inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable. When 'tis examined without prejudice, with a ſincere Deſire to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into it, at the firſt unveiling you find it venerable for its Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, pure in its Morals, ſublime in its Myſteries, divine in its Source. What ſurer Courſe can we then ſteer, than to ſubmit our ſelves to the Law of a God, who after having eſtabliſhed his Church in the midſt of Idolatrous People, in ſpite of all worldly Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, has obliged thoſe very Men,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96673:12"/>notwithſtanding their Pride and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſions, to acknowledge him for their Creator, and to pay him the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration which he juſtly claims? What can we do more becoming rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Men, than to embrace a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine confirm'd by ſo many Miracles, born up with the Teſtimony of ſo many Martyrs, taught uniformly du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo many Ages, defended by ſo many Great Men, as famous for the Purity of their Manners, as for the Solidity of their Judgment, and the Profoundneſs of their Learning? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Faith, Love muſt be annexed, and the Fear of God; the Love of him to make all our Actions ſubſervient to his Glory, and the Fear of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to retain us in the Rounds of Duty, when his Love is not ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to ſtop the Fierceneſs of our Paſſions: 'Tis this Love mixed with an uſeful Fear, inlightened by Faith, and animated by Hope, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Virtue of a true Chriſtian, and which conſummates his peculiar Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96673:13"/>a Character infinitely more Glorious than all others, and which alone worthily maintained, is able to procure us unperiſhable Felicity. Thoſe who adore Jeſus Chriſt as their God, and who are engaged notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in Hereſie, flatter themſelves in vain to arrive at this Sovereign Happineſs; for we learn of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Maſter, that there is but one way to attain it, which cannot be the way of thoſe that go every one their own way, abandoning the Catholick Church, which is the only Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt, the only Depoſitory of his Will, and the faithful Interpreter of his Word. Let us then remain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably adhering to the Holy Church, 'tis thereby that Men will deliver themſelves from Doubts, quiet the Remorſes , ſtifle the Troubles and Diſorders wherewith Hereticks and Unbelievers are agitated. 'Tis by this, I ſay, that in the important Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Religion, our Lives glide in a ſweet and calm Security. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96673:13"/>let us not believe that our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs depends only on our Faith, without the Concurrence of our Works; an Acknowledgment muſt be paid for the Heaps of Favours which the Almighty does confer, 'tis he who hath made us what we are, our Bodies and our Souls are the Workmanſhip of his Hands, our Virtues are the Gifts of his Grace, our Temporal Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages are but the repeated Streams which flow from his inexhauſtible Bounty; 'tis he who ſupports us in Temptations, who fortifies us in Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, who comforts us in Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents; 'tis he laſtly, who has devoted his Son to Death for our Redemption, and who has prepared an eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for the faithful Obſervers of his Laws. Let us not be inſenſible of ſuch a Throng of Gifts, and ſince God only expects the return of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Heart, let us love our Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor ſo exalted, and ſo amiable; let us obey his Commands, and perſuade our ſelves that no real Pleaſure, or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96673:14"/>true Satisfaction can be found, but in an intire Submiſſion to his Adorable Will.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Honoring of Parents.</head>
               <p>THis is not, to ſpeak properly, ſo much a Preceptive Maxim, as an inviolable Law, which has ever been obſerved, as well by Barbarous, as the moſt Refined Nations; which is a plain Argument, that a Law ſo engraven in Mens Hearts is no other than what is natural. On the other ſide, God who knew that the Voice of Nature is not loud enough to be heard by Men in the Hurry of their Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, has given them an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to honor their Parents, and threatens them with the ſevereſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, if they ever dare break
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96673:14"/>through the Tye of this Command. Our own Reaſon at firſt ſight diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the Juſtice of this Precept; for is there any thing more equitable than to pay our Reſpects, and devote our Services to them, who next to God Almighty have conferred a Being on and in our defenceleſs years guarded us by their Cares? Let Children and more eſpecially thoſe of an illuſtrious Deſcent, who ought to have more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Inclinations than others) not fail to make the Duty of Obedience as bright in the Practice, as 'tis lawful in the Obligation: And if they will not draw down upon themſelves the direful Effects of an incenſed God, and be publickly ſtigmatized with the Brand of Ungrateful, or rather Unnatural, not worthy to load the Earth; let 'em always preſerve the Sentiments of Love to their Parents undiminiſhed, and never relinquiſh the Submiſſion, and grateful Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment wherewith undeſigning Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rure has inſpired 'em.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96673:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Importance of Education.</head>
               <p>CHildren without doubt have out-grown their Innocence when they have weakened their Reſpect to their Fathers in any part, but their Guilt ſwells when they have heedleſly with cool Advances drown'd that Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which they owe: But Fathers, who at random bring up their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are not much leſs criminal, ſince it may be ſaid, that for the moſt part, the Happineſs or Unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Life depends upon Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A wicked Diſpoſition is the fruitful Original of all Vices, if there be not a laborious Application to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and turn it into a new Track. A ſine Genius uncultivated, pitiably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it ſelf, and at an Age when the Paſſions are ſo fierce, a Heart flatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d by the Smoothneſs of inviting Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures delivers it ſelf up at a ſhort
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96673:15"/>Parley, when there is no kind Informer to alarm it with the Poiſon that is under 'em. We ſee but too often the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Effects of an unpoliſhed Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A young Man who has never been acquainted with Knowledge or Deſert, is unfit to enter upon any Employment, his Paſſions (whoſe full Swinge he indulgeth) engaging him to ſpend his Eſtate, to riſque all for their Gratification, and at the ſame time to contemn and hate all the World; his Diſorders never miſs of involving him in Troubles, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they are carried to that heighth, that he thereby tarniſhes the Glory of his Family, and everlaſtingly buries his Reputation. What a gnawing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content haunts the Father who has disfigured his Son's Mind, in not ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning him with Inſtruction, not fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing him with Piety, by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe Helps for the Regulating his Manners and Demeanour, which he was indiſpenſably obliged to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter? But the Joy is all Rapture which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96673:16"/>flows in upon a Parent, who, after by his own ſedulous Application he has form'd the Underſtanding, and mould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Faculties of his Son, ſees him no ſooner launch'd into the World, but he is fluſh'd in univerſal eſteem; that all civil Men are fond of him, that he diſtinguiſhes his Performance in the firſt Employments he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, derives an Honor on his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily by his fine Accompliſhments, and every day more confirms the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of his Virtue, Wiſdom and Abilities. Sec what is the Product of a good Education, a ſedateneſs in this Life, and the Felicity of the other are inſeparable from it. Fathers then are to leave no Stone unturn'd, nor to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover any Parſimony, when 'tis to ſet out their Children with Advantage in the Voyage of the World; and Children ought to look upon that time ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable which is employed to inſtruct them in their Duties, and to lay ſuch neceſſary Principles into 'em, of which they themſelves will own the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96673:16"/>Benefit in the ſeveral Stages of their Lives. They are obliged, I ſay, to ſecond by their induſtrious Purſuit, and by their Tractableneſs to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage that Care which is taken of their Education; ſince that is an Affair which aims directly at their Good, and in which they are more intereſted that any others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> What a Young Gentleman ought to Learn.</head>
               <p>THE Variety of Truths in every Science is wrapt up in Difficulties, and as the Bent of our Diſpoſitions ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth us to a Diſcovery, ſo there is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways a Satisfaction that ſufficiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrains us in our Reſearches after it. But yet all Sciences are not to be courted with an equal Paſſion; ſome are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96673:17"/>modiſh, and we learn 'em only for Divertiſement; but there are others which are neceſſary, and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for a Man of Quality. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, Politicks and Hiſtory are of that ſort; the firſt plants ſteddy Rules in his Mind, by which he is to ſquare his Behaviour; the other two acquaint him with the Rocks where other young Beginners have been ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd.</p>
               <p>Mathematicks contain ſo many convincing Diſcoveries, they reliſh ſo well with the Palate of this Age, that at the leaſt 'tis requiſite to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the eaſieſt and moſt uſeful part of them, as Arithmetick, Geography, and the Doctrine of the Sphere; to which we may ſubjoin a ſlender Familiarity with Geometry, which makes them who drudge after it reſerv'd, and circumſpect in their Judgments, teacheth them in their Queſt of all ſorts of Truths to mingle an exact Method, and which inures them to keep the Mind intent, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96673:17"/>eager, a thing ſo eſſential to gain Sciences, and tranſact Buſieſs. 'Tis yet of more moment to be Maſter of true Rhetorick, I mean that which does not only inſtruct a Man to ſpeak ſmoothly, but to carry away his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience with a perſuaſive Force; this taking Art upon ſome nicking Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, is ſtrangely ſignificant, where blundering Courage and blunt Valour are baffled; this skillfully inſinuates it ſelf into the Soul of Princes and great Men, Manages Friends, Enemies, Strangers, uncontroulably conquers Hearts, damps popular Fury, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſtops the Torrent of a fluſh'd Armies Rage. Philoſophy alſo muſt not be excluded, it goes a great way in faſhioning of the Mind, it gives it Wings, and more elevates the Flights of it; Logick and Metaphyſicks make a Man more Juſt, and more Acute; and natural Philoſophy, by unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Secrets of Nature, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Beauty, the Order, and the admirable Harmony of the ſeveral
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96673:18"/>Parts of the Univerſe to a Man's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, influenceth him at the ſame time to adore the Author of ſuch a marvellous Compoſure, The Study of the Tongues is to uſher in the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of more ſerious Sciences, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Morality, whoſe Principal Rules can never be learn'd too ſoon: The manly Exerciſes of the Body are not to be neglected, they keep it in good Repair, they ſtrengthen the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſcatter a free Air through all a Man's Addreſs, and a certain Grace which ſurprizingly takes at firſt ſight; which is no little Advantage in the World. I do not ſpeak here of Sciences proper for each Order of Men, I ſuppoſe a Man deſign'd to ſerve the Church is to dive into the Bottom of Divinity; a Man of the Long Robe to pry into worm-eaten Laws, and ſuperannuated Cuſtoms, and a Sword-Man to cut his Way into all Military Knowledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96673:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> What ought to be the Scope of his Studies.</head>
               <p>ACtions which in themſelves would challenge Eſteem, are ſtrip'd of this Privilege when they are founded on ill Principles. To undertake Study is of it ſelf an Employment decent, and honorable; but one ought to obſerve exactly what Spring 'tis that turns the Engine, 'tis commonly to be puft up with the popular Guſts of vain Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, or to exalt themſelves to ſome advantageous Poſt, or to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the Publick in Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the Directions of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which would have every one exert all the Powers of their Souls, and diſplay the Vigor of every Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent they have received. The two
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96673:19"/>firſt Motives are baſe and unmanly; 'twere better never to be ſtudious, than to be indebted to Oſtentation and Intereſt for the being ſo. The third being the eaſie Suggeſtion of the Law of Nature, and the Genuine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of innate Religion, is valuable, and worthy of the Purſuit of a Noble Mind; ſo that thoſe who are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Education of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ought ſeaſonably to inform them, that their Studies cannot be well employed, if they do not ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate in the Glory of God; if they do not tend to their own Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to the Publick Good of the Community where they live.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96673:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> To make a Right Uſe of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</head>
               <p>I Am of Opinion, that they who would plead for any Priority of Eſteem upon the Account of their Birth, or their advanced Poſt in the World, muſt, by a proportionable Extent of Knowledge, ſhew that they are fairly intitled to it; at leaſt it will be allowed, that the Improvement of Reaſon is highly advantageous to a Man of Quality, provided that he applies it dextrouſly; and inſtead of being conceited of his own Acquire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, makes uſe of 'em only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate his Mind, and to perfect his Underſtanding: For this Reaſon let a Man have never ſuch a Latitude of Capacity, he ought at no time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96673:20"/>to hale his Learning on the Stage, nor to diſpute eagerly for Triſles, nor to impoſe his own Senſe on every Body, and grate upon the Ears of Company with a dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Tone; this pedantick Way is never digeſted by Men of Senſe. The penetrating into Learning refines our Manners, inſpires us with the Sweetneſs of Addreſs, gives us Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Circumſpection. So we ſee commonly, that where Knowledge is exalted to the true Pitch, a great deal of Moderation, Humility and Wiſdom is intermix'd with it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as ſuch Mens Souls have a ſort of Expanſion beyond others, ſo they more ſuddenly diſcover, either the Ornaments that poliſh, or the Flaws which ſubject their Minds to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual Thruſts of Calumny and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96673:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> What a Man is to do for bis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</head>
               <p>THE Laws of Nature, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, oblige us to pay our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations that Reſpect which they may challenge; to defend their Honor, to ſuſtain their Intereſt when we may do it juſtly; for beſides that it is our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to be ſtrictly united in the moſt endearing Ties to thoſe who are allied in Blood to us, it carries a mighty Stream of Advantages along with it; you ſeldom ſee Families ſo cemented, ſurprizingly blown up: They mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſupport and cheriſh one another, either by themſelves, or by the Train of numerous Friends which they draw after 'em; and this harmonious Intelligence preſerves both in Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96673:21"/>and Authority in the World. Put caſe our Kindred had not ſo much Deſert to invite our Reſpect, yet Decency and Charity forbid our Breaking with 'em; their Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections ought not to make us inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but rather generouſly to cover in them what we our ſelves have a Regret to ſee, and to clap in with every Opportunity to do 'em Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> To be Subject to the Laws of the Country.</head>
               <p>THE Divine Prerogative, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Civil Society, and the Publick Good do require that every individual Member in a Community ſhould ſubmit himſelf to the Laws of it: In a Monarchy Subjects are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96673:21"/>to honor and revere their King: and in Commonwealths, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, by Compact, lay Claim to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. In both, the Duty is indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſable; and 'tis a Law that has always been ſtamp'd with the Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of every Clime. Whatſoever has been authoriz'd in a State by long Continuance, is not to be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide to Humour an ambitious Freak, or a popular Maggot, nor to undergo any Change, but for Reaſons more weighty than thoſe which contributed to its firſt Eſtabliſhment; for People who would not be chous'd of a well grounded Settlement, had need make ſharp Inquiries, whether the ſpecious Project of a Reformer does not juſtle out that univerſal Repoſe which they who before enjoy'd it, are equally ſtill oblig'd to promote. Innovations which private ſelf-intereſted Men would introduce into the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Kingdom, have often un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hing'd a Regular Frame; but we rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hear that they corroborate the old,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96673:22"/>or inlarge the Power of any Realm. Hiſtory ſwells with Examples which clinch this Truth. How unanimouſly have Civil Laws ever paſt Sentence on Rebellion, tho it has been gilded with the faireſt Colours which could be laid on. 'Tis atteſted by the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of all Ages, that the horrible Ills which Inteſtine Wars do produce, are a greater Burthen on any People, than thoſe which they may ſometimes riſque to incurr from their Prince, by his holding the Ballance of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, with ſome Unevenneſs, and ſeeming Partiality. Beſides, if every ſorry Pretender of Grievances, ſhould have Licenſe to diſobey his Superiors whenſoever he had a Mind to be deliver'd of a Complaint, (which all Rebels ſuppoſe themſelves privileg'd to do) farewel Society, for no Form of Rule can ſubſiſt on theſe extravagant Terms, ſince every one hurried by his Paſſions, would never want plauſible Reaſons whereon to ground his Plea of oppoſing the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96673:22"/>moſt lawful Powers that ever were. So that however they who are Cloth'd. with Sovereign Authority may miſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy it, People have no more to do but to be eaſie within the Bounds of their Duty and Obedience, let 'em from thence acknowledge, that God by the Proportion of his Chaſtiſement ſeems irritated; and therefore as he diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of the Hearts of Kings, muſt be ſupplicated to enrich their Princes Minds with ſuch neceſſary Virtues, as may induce 'em to Govern with an equal Mixture of Clemency and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. In the mean time that Nation we may call Happy, where a King careſſes his Subjects, as his Children; and they again, as to an indulgent Father, pay back the acceptable Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage which they owe. Happy is that Realm where the Prince with indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Application propagates the Wellfare of thoſe under his Care; and at the ſame time thoſe who Bask themſelves under that Sun-ſhine, ſmother the Popular Guſts early, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96673:23"/>they become Gloomy Clouds, big with impending Ruine, to darken the Luſtre of Royal Grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The Duty of Allegiance is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Law.</head>
               <p>THis Maxim naturally ſprings from the foregoing; for the Laws of all Countries oblige us to obey the King, (as Streams gratefully to own the Fountain from whence they do derive) and forbid us entring into any Engagements that by the wideſt Conſtruction might ſeem to claſh with that firſt Devoir. Now ſuch as by an implicit Surrender devote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves entirely to the Diſpoſal of any Perſon who is elevated either by Birth, or Office, to a Station ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to 'em, are in great danger to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96673:23"/>ſtrip themſelves of their Fidelity to their Liege Lord, when their Leader (who ought to animate the Allegiance of the Lower Orders of Men) becomes himſelf the firſt Deſerter. Therefore wiſe Men have always diſapproved theſe too ſtrict Confederacies, and thoſe private Alliances that ſhould at any time claſh with our Natural Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations. 'Tis enough if I give a Miniſter of State the Reſpect that is due to his lofty Seat, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming ſo much his Vaſſal, as to ſell him that Liberty of mine, of which my Sovereign only is the Maſter. 'Tis not I that blame in general a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference that is paid to great Men, if their Authoritative Influence does not Hand over Head betray us to comply with their Criminal Paſſions; for if there be no Repugnancy to our Duty, who can condemn it? 'Tis worth the while therefore to obſerve whether the Grandees themſelves are Loyal, and true to the Intereſt of their Sovereign, and whether there is not a Snake un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96673:24"/>the Graſs, and that under the Pretence of communicating Favours to us, they have not a crafty Deſign to hook us into an Aſſociation that undermines the Throne of our Prince, and is a forward ſtep towards his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing. But if we get any Light that they drive at ſo black an Attempt, 'tis then we muſt with eager Haſte retreat from the Perfidious, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſacrifice to our Duty the Hope of any Glittering Advantage what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; beſides, the Golden Promiſes, which thoſe Grandees, who are the Heads of Parties, make, prove for the moſt part a Fairy-Land; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being able to aſſiſt others, theſe empty Politicians are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with every revengeful Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, they precipitate thoſe who adhere to the Wheel of their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; and both, at laſt, ſink under the Puniſhment which they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch pains to deſerve. Let us then be perſuaded, that whatſoever Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions ſtart up in a Realm, 'tis always
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96673:24"/>beſt, inviolably to ſtick to the King; for as his Side is the juſteſt, ſo the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of cleaving to it will be the moſt honorable, and ſatisfactory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Againſt thoſe who dare cenſure the Government.</head>
               <p>'TIS only the Effect of a giddy Preſumption that ſpirits on tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous Subjects to quarrel with the Adminiſtration of the State, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining that publick Aſſairs would roll more ſmoothly if they were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagged by their fanciful Schemes, whereas 'tis their Duty to ſubmit to the Laws, and to baniſh murmuring, and ſtifle Oppoſition, when a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to their Regulations is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. If Abuſes do inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into any Government, and by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96673:25"/>length of time encroach upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; no doubt we ought to wiſh they were Reformed; but the Means to do it are ſo very difficult, that to undertake it without a Lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, would tend rather to the ſhaking of the Monarchy, than the amending its Defects. 'Tis an Inſolence in private Men to brand the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which they live under. 'Tis the Buſineſs of the King and his Miniſters to examine if there be any Diſorders in the Community uncorrected; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, if the particular Aſſemblies of the Eſtates, which are held in different Places, find out any Miſcarriages in their reſpective Provinces, they may make uſe of the Authority which the King allows 'em for their Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and tho this Authority ſhould prove inſufficient for that End, and that the Blots we would clear, ſtill remain, we ought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his Majeſty with the Iſſue of our Endeavours, that he may give conſent for the Preſcription of new
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96673:25"/>Remedies, moſt for the Eaſe and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of his People; but after all that State-menders can alledge, the King is to remain the Judge of any Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and tho he ſhould not agree to ſuch Demands as carry a fair Plauſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Right for their being granted, ſtill we ought to acquieſce with this Confidence, that his Non-concurrence Is for die real Good of his Subjects, tho the Reaſons are behind the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to us, they are evident and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative to himſelf and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96673:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Againſt the Fomenters of Plots and Diſturbances.</head>
               <p>'TIS eaſie to make a Judgment from the foregoing Principles, what a great Deal they have to anſwer for, who by that State-craft of preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for Redreſs of Grievances, raiſe State Hurricanes, and by an unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiable Revolt ſtir up ſuch Commoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as ſometimes ſhatter the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, and (as our own Memories 100 ſadly can inform us) often entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deface, and overturn it. When theſe dangerous Incendiaries firſt ſet out, the greateſt Sticklers for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation amongſt 'em, to awe the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, take great pains to ſhew themſelves diſaffected, hoping that they ſhall be taken off by Court-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96673:26"/>and gratified by profitable Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments only for being tolerably honeſt. 'Tis a falſe Step in the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and an unwarrantable Reach of Subtilty, which puts Men on ſuch ſharking Methods to mount them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves near the Helm; Experience tells us, that this Cunning is not crown'd with Succeſs, but much otherwiſe; and that more commonly the wild Purſuers draw down the Ruinous Conſequences on their own Heads. The Strength of theſe Reaſons, and above all, the Eagerneſs to do our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ought to oblige us conſtantly to reject with Diſdain all ſuch Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as are oppoſite to it, and to avoid even the leaſt Occaſions which might call our Fidelity in queſtion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96673:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> The True Way to gain Eſteem.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing which ſweetens the Toil of Life ſo well, as to know how to win the Love of thoſe you converſe with. He that is a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of this Sort, can ſcarce tread the Stage unſucceſsfully, becauſe the World is Crowded with his protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friends: but you will ſay, how ſhall a Man get admiſſion to a Heart, which it is ſo difficult effectually to conquer? 'Tis not a Task ſo inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable as you imagine; the fitteſt Qualification to ſet up with, is Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; it makes the Mind pliable, ready to embrace Inſtruction, generally plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; it takes off our Ruggedneſs in oppoſing others, and makes us ſtoop to all Humours, as far as the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:96673:27"/>of our Duty will give leave; Complaiſance, and the Impreſſions which it naturally makes in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit of our Life, repays us with a plentiful Benevolence in the Receivers. Sincerity alſo has a great Stroke in engaging the Affection and Truſt of thoſe we keep company with; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that you do not ſeparate this Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from Prudence, and Diſcretion. A bountiful Temper makes the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtill more aſſured over another's Soul; for at the very minute we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Man ſerviceable and friendly to us, we cannot ſhift off our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of loving him before we know him; and his Character, which we have already begun to dreſs up with ſo many Advantages, wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his Preſence to complete it. To theſe various Methods of acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Reſpect, we may add one which ſeems to comprehend all the reſt: Would you be beloved of others? Shew them firſt the Example your Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Value for them will ſtrangely
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96673:28"/>whet 'em to Imitation. The Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of being lov'd is ſo ſweet, that you muſt love irreſiſtably in your Turn, and make the Party who occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions it your Favourite. Theſe are ſome of the general ways made uſe of by ſuch as would inſinuate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the good Opinion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Moſt Men are remiſs in ſailing by this Compaſs, and then 'tis no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if ſo many daſh themſelves againſt the fatal Rocks. I do not ſet down the particular Means which may be made uſe of to be riveted in the Love of Men; this depends on their Age, their Humour, the Poſture of their Affairs, and the different Turns of their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. I only add, that almoſt all have a blind ſide, one domineering Paſſion, where, if you attack 'em, they lie open, and unguarded, and conſequently are quickly taken by ſurprize; but as that very Paſſion is commonly exorbitant, no Man ought to be ſuch a Coward as to flatter 'em where they are leaſt defencible, to gain
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96673:28"/>ſome diſhononorable End we have to ſerve; for this would be to break through the Laws of Honor, found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Principles of Chriſtian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, which could never countenance any wicked Means, tho it were to help forward the juſteſt Undertaking whatſoever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Of High Birth and Reputation.</head>
               <p>IT were much better for a Man of Quality to loſe his Life, than loſe his Honor by any reproachful Action; and the more illuſtriouſly he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, the more Guilt he derives upon himſelf if he degenerates from the Virtue of his Anceſtors: Great Wealth, Dignity, and being nobly Born, which exalt the Merit of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons already in Eſtimation, only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96673:29"/>to ſwell the Confuſion and Shame of thoſe who have buried their Credit by the Repetition of their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies; how can ſo many Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple then aſſume the Pretence of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when at the ſame time they are the Scandal of Chriſtianity, and act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Worth of a Modeſt Man? Do they take their Honor to be an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary Eſtate, and that the Glory of their Predeceſſors ſhall redound to their Advantage, ſo long as they have Vices enough to cloud the others Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality; and (if it were poſſible by unhallowed Practices) to unembalm their Memories? True Nobleneſs, and real Grandeur has its Reſidence in the Soul; and if in any inſtance we give Gentlemen the upper Hand of Plebeians, 'tis becauſe we ſuppoſe 'em ſtock'd with-Endowments ſuitable to their illuſtrious Original; a happy Mixture of Uprightneſs, Generoſity, Courage, actual Bravery, conſpicuous Loyalty to their Prince, and hearty Zeal for their Countries Good, make
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96673:29"/>up that glorious Compoſition, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth them from the Level of other Men. 'Tis by the Practice of theſe Virtues that Men confeſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Heroes out-done, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend their Pedigree with more Advantage, and outſhine the Luſtre of thoſe who lived before 'em. But then let 'em reflect, that their ſtanding is ſo rickliſh at that heighth, that one ill Action is ſufficient to mine a Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that has been building up many years; and what ill luck it is, that a Man ſhould part with a little <hi>Indies,</hi> only to take the Range of a Libertine, and to ſurrender his Reaſon a Captive to wild Paſſion; if young Gentlemen would but conſider how ſerviceable a fair Reputation is; doubtleſs, they would be better Husbands of it, and not laviſh it away with ſuch a cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary Prodigality. Let 'em caſt their Eyes around, and ſee if any thing gives equal Acceſs to the good Graces of the Prince, 'tis this that is the Inlet to Advancement both in Camp and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:96673:30"/>Court; 'tis this makes Merit ſterling, which is idolized every where. To conclude, 'tis this which begets Friends, and to which all contribute their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and Regards.</p>
               <p>But one who lies under the Scandal of Diſhoneſty, draws upon himſelf univerſal Hatred, and Contempt; he is fled from as a Peſt, no Body will entertain Converſation with him; he muſt not pretend to be a Favourite of his Prince, or his Miniſters; for who cares to prefer him whom he doth not value, but by conſequence ſuſpects? So that there are no Gifts, no Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that a Man without Honor can hope for, if he has a great; Eſtate, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome miſerable Slaves to Intereſt will ſtick to him, but he will never muſter one true Friend, but always ſee himſelf under a Sentence of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment from the Society of Honeſt Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96673:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Of the Choice of a Station in the World.</head>
               <p>TO chuſe precipitately that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Life from which a Man is never to be divorced whilſt he breaths in this Lower Region, is an Action that has as much danger as weight in it, a Man ought not to come to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination about it, till he has made the utmoſt Scrutiny into his own Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, his Abilities, the Suitableneſs of his Talents, and afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd whether from the united Force of all theſe, he is capable to diſcharge all the Offices which the Profeſſion he would embrace, neceſſarily doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge from him. And if he is able to undergo the Fatigue and Pains that he muſt encounter, if he will be faithful
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96673:31"/>in the executing of it; 'Tis good upon ſuch an occaſion, to take along with you the Thoughts of a diſcreet and knowing Friend; unveil to him with Confidence your moſt private Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Caſe. As the fixing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Employment is the greateſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair of a Man's Life, his firſt Care ought to be to conſult God about it, to deſire his Benevolent Concurrence; for without that Divine Direction, 'tis impoſſible to fathom what Courſe of Life Providence has deſign'd you to purſue. Every one ought to be very jealous of himſelf, and narrowly to obſerve the Tendency of his Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, becauſe 'tis to be feared the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs of the Age may influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence our Natural Genius to that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, as to ſway it to enter upon this important Choice for bare Temporal Ends, without looking to the grand Point we have to negotiate, our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Be ſure, that Self-Love has no ſhare in any Reſolution you ſhall take in ſo nice a Juncture. But if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96673:31"/>having ſeann'd duly all Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, you do not find that God calls you to another way of Living, you ought to acquieſce in that wherein you were bred. But to diſpoſe otherwiſe of himſelf without ſuch an Intimation, to make Vows, to change Profeſſions, and the Road of Life We have troden, is rather a fallacious Cure for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, than any real promoting of a Man's Happineſs. When a Man rambles from one Eſtate to another, he riſques a great Deal by the Change, at leaſt if he does not do it by the known Rules of avowed Wiſdom. Be very wary therefore in changing your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, for a fooliſh Whim, or to ſooth a weak Paſſion; ſuch an Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſeldom proves happy; but is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten followed by a Long Repentance, if Reaſon enlighten'd by Faith doth not judge it both neceſſary and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96673:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> To be Vigilant, Intent, and Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.</head>
               <p>IF a Man would do a Thing well, let him ſpare no Application to Complete it; for if we ſee Men of the beſt parts (after all the Sedulity and Drudging you can imagine) miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry in the finiſhing of what they had projected, what Succeſs can a ſlender Wit expect, that is Loitering and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy in the Purſuit? When a Man puſhes at Advancement in the World, a thouſand Rubs encounter him in the Road, no Man ever aim'd at a Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phal Chariot, but thoſe who envied him, would be ſure always to clog the Wheels. What is more common than to ſee Rivals juſtling to get that Poſt they ſee others aſpiring to? They
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:96673:32"/>that are before do all they can to clip the Wings of ſuch as are ſluttering to mount; and they that follow a Riſing Man, leſt they ſhould lag a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, make the ſwifteſt Efforts to overtake him; they that go along with him labour to out-run him: Now how is it poſſible to defeat all theſe Enemies, without ſummoning all our Warineſs to aſſiſt us? Beſides, we live in an Age that will not be put off with what our Fore-Fathers would have digeſted; nothing but what is excellent, and ſuperlatively fine in its kind, will engage the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of thoſe we have to do with; any thing that is but indifferent, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thrown back with Diſdain, or at moſt but very coldly received. Now let a Man have never ſuch a towring Genius, 'tis almoſt impoſſible to arrive at Perfection in any thing without an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme Study for the Maſtery; 'tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an impotent Flattery of ones ſelf, to conceive one can ſtart up a topping Man, unleſs he be tenaciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:96673:33"/>to take a great Deal of Pains for the Character.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Of the First Undertakings.</head>
               <p>'TIS a common Maxim, but of great Uſe, that a Man ought to lay a good Foundation before he attempts to erect any Building, ſo that he may ward himſelf againſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches it a Miſcarriage ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. A Man ought to rally all his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that he may not be baffled in his firſt Enterprizes. 'Tis generally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that a Man's future Fortune, and Reputation are flouriſhing in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to his Succeſs at his firſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out. If he be unſucceſsful at the firſt ſtep, his Judgment is call'd in queſtion; and 'tis preſently imputed to his want of Conduct, ſo that they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96673:33"/>are jealous of truſting him a ſecond time with any Employment conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able enough to give him an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to ſignalize himſelf; for inſtance, in the Army ſuch a hot-headed young Fellow fought unſeaſonably at ſuch a place, undoubtedly his Raſhneſs would diſappoint that hopeful Deſign we have in hand: 'Tis much more eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to give the Command to one that has more Diſcretion to execute it, when all this while the forward Spark was not to blame; he was not juſtly chargeable with the Fault they lay upon him, he behav'd himſelf like a good Officer, all is one, if he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his firſt Aim, that ſhall juſtifie his Accuſation of Imprudence. Now ſince the World is unjuſt enough ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to condemn even thoſe who are Innocent, what Pardon will there be allow'd to thoſe who misbehave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the firſt time they are em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd? The Impreſſions that are made ſo early, laſt ſo long, that a young Gentleman can't be too ſollicitous to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96673:34"/>begin well All will conjecture, by the early Budding, how you will flouriſh afterwards.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Which is the beſt Way to gain the Eſteem of Princes and Great Men.</head>
               <p>'TIS as Glorious to purchaſe our Sovereign's Applauſe by ſine Actions, as 'tis ſhameful to entitle our ſelves to his Smiles, by ſneaking Compliances and mean Flatteries: A Gentleman at Court ought to bear up his Character with Honor, nor to let any Intereſt out-ſway the Obligations he has, to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unworthy of his Quality. He that would ſerve Perſons in this exalted Sphere, muſt give larger Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of his Deference to, and his Regards for 'em; he ought plainly to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96673:34"/>pull off the Diſguiſe from thoſe Truths which others maſque, and of which it is of exceeding Moment they ſhould be informed; but yet it is to be done with ſuch Care, and dutiful Reſpect, that it may ſeem to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ſincere Product of Standard-Allegiance: He that adheres to this Management, falls very rarely in Diſgrace, becauſe his Actions com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves; 'tis true, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Plain-dealing is offenſive; yet when 'tis accompanied with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and a due Mixture of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, and has alſo a ſolid Virtue for its Baſis, Princes and Great Men, who have an innate Generoſity, will cheriſh it more than you would imagine. But fulſom Flatteries are their Averſion, they deſpiſe thoſe who are guilty of 'em, as ſordid Souls, who will ſtick at no Baſeneſs, if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may preſerve their preſent For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, or mend it. Princes know exactly to diſtinguiſh an Honeſt Man, on whom they may with Security re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:96673:35"/>from a fawning Courtier who has only a Weather-Cock-Loyalty, that will ſhift about when his Intereſt is in danger. 'Tis a wrong Courſe then to acquire the Eſtimation of Great Men by creeping in their Preſence, and humouring them with the poor Arts of Servility. A Man who plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honors 'em, and ſerves 'em when Occaſion is offer'd, but who is down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, ſincere, and whoſe Duty no Conſideration can ſeparate from his Principles, pleaſeth 'em better, and they will more readily prefer him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:96673:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> Of the Advantages of true Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</head>
               <p>MEthinks one may make a better Judgment of the Bleſſing of a true Friend, if he does but conſider the Condition of that Man who is ſtrip'd of all; he is even an Exile in his own Country, and when he is in the greateſt need to be ſupported by Counſel, and Aſſiſtance, he has no Refuge to befriend him, no Sanctuary either to revive his Hopes, or calm his Fears; if any good Luck befals him, it alters the Caſe but a very little; for the Senſe that no Body is a Sharer with him in it, ſwallows up the greateſt part of the ſatisfaction: and if he be out of Favour, 'tis more difficult to bear the Diſgrace, becauſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96673:36"/>he is over-loaded with a Burthen which it requires more than one to ſtand under; but a faithful Friend is Co-partner with us both in Joy and Grief, he makes us eaſie in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, raiſeth our proſtrate Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and like a Man of Honor ſtakes down his own Credit and Eſtate to make our tottering Fortune ſteddy. The interpoſing of a Friend's. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel makes the Current of our Affairs glide more ſmoothly; his ſtaid Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces oblige us to rectifie what is amiſs in our Manners, and blameable in our Deportment. But without enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any more of the good Offices we are indebted for to a Friend, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely taking is the Pleaſure that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from Friendſhip barely ſo called? 'Tis certainly one of the higheſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments of Life to Love, and be Beloved. Nothing is ſo agreeable as this Union of the Wills, and that Harmony of the Sentiments as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways found betwixt two true Friends. What is there more charming, than
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96673:36"/>that Reciprocal and undiſgniſed Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing of one anothers moſt retired Thoughts? And yet all I have ſaid, is but an imperfect Repreſentation of the Benefit and Delights of true Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; our Expreſſions are too flat and pinion'd, and we cannot riſe high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to deſcribe 'em, and no Man can ſpeak pertinently of 'em who has not lov'd a Friend to an exalted Pitch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> Of the Choice of a Friend.</head>
               <p>THE Advantages of a well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friendſhip are not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, but that the Hazards to which a falſe Friend expoſeth us, are as great; for beſides that in ſome ſort we are made accountable for his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, he engageth us in perplex'd Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and involves us in the ſame Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:96673:37"/>he has drawn by Imprudence upon himſelf; 'tis therefore of great Conſequence not to contract Friendſhip but with a Man who has the neceſſary Qualifications of a ſtanch Friend; the chiefeſt and moſt eſſential of 'em is Piety, for without that Cement the ſtricteſt Friendſhip is but a Rope of Sand; there is no other Tye ſufficient to prevent a Diſſolution of it; the jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and contrariety of the Paſſions will quickly diſunite ſuch as only Intereſt holds together, or ſome other Motive yet more pernicious: But 'tis requiſite, that the Friend we pitch upon, beſides Piety, be ſtored with Wiſdom, and a ſharp inſight into things; for that, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Prudence, will not do his Buſineſs in the World; let his Soul be ſoft, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that it be ſtedfaſt and gallant the ſame time; let him be courteous, modeſt, and of a frank Temper, with a good Command over his Paſſions, firm in his Duty; and to ſumm up all, he muſt be completely an Honeſt Man. If we our ſelves poſſeſs theſe recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96673:37"/>Qualities, we ſhall never think our ſelves well match'd but with a Friend of this Character; and a Friendſhip ſo well ſettled, will mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advance our own Happineſs; but is there ſuch a Rarity to be found? I confeſs, 'tis difficult to find ſo many Accompliſhments concentred in a ſingle Perſon; after all, if he be not wholly Angelick, his Converſation will much becalm our Minds; if we find in his Soul a plentiful Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Piety, Diſcretion, Civility, and Conſtant Attendance on his Duty, we muſt reſolve to paſs over the other concomitant Imperfections; for as we are not without ours, and are deſirous to meet with the charitable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of others, 'tis but Juſtice that in our Turns we ſhould have ſome Indulgence for the ſmall Eſcapes of Friends, when there is ſo much ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundant Merit in other Inſtances that adds a Luſtre to all they do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:96673:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> Of the Good, and Ill Uſe of Time.</head>
               <p>THere is no way ſo certain to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive at Tranquillity in this Life, and to aſſure our Happineſs in the next, as a thrifty Employment of our Time; wherefore, in my Opinion, this is to be done. A Man muſt ſet upon Study, and proportion it to the Proſpects he has in the World, and the Condition he deſigns to embark in; he muſt chuſe firſt wiſely what he will Read, and then do it methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; let him meditate at his leiſure; and as he ſhould dote on Truth, let him follow it through all Diſguiſes. Let him converſe often with the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, dive into Men in general, and himſelf in particular, and acquaint
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96673:38"/>himſelf exactly with the Buſineſs he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to follow; and when he is once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, let him diſcharge his Obligations exactly; but as (if we do not move upon good Principles) we cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe our Happineſs to be well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, our fundamental Care ought to be to love God, to ſerve him in a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Current of Duty, to bring all our Actions to that Teſt whether they do ſet forward his Glory. They who ſpend their Time ſo, never are tired, but live in the greateſt Sedateneſs; they fill their Minds with abundance of uſeful and entertaining Knowledge, which ſatisfactorily buſies 'em when they are alone, which makes 'em ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to their Country, which tends to poliſh their Manners, and direct their Affairs, and procures all Perſons of Merit to be their Advocates; but they that immerſe themſelves in Pleaſures, and lay aſide their uſeful Endeavours, and commendable La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, fall even below Scorn: as theſe People for the moſt part are ſo ſunk
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96673:39"/>into the Ignorance of what they are to do, and will never look home where their Stock is ſo poor, they drop in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly into Debauchery, which after it has infected their Mind, ſpreads a Contagion into their Underſtanding, and plunges 'em in Libertiniſm and Impiety; ſo that their Life which was at firſt but a dead Weight, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in the beginning, becomes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards guilty, and in the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences always unhappy. Since then the Reſult of yawning Idleneſs is ſo fatal, and that by making uſe of our Time well, we reap ſo many Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, is it not extremely ſurprizing, that moſt Men are unconcern'd for this Trifling; that they only take pains to get it off their Hands; and that they can be ſo ſenſeleſs as blindly to tread the Path of Life, and reſolve to do nothing for God, the publick, or themſelves. Let us not be imprudent to this heighth, to commit a Fault of this Magnitude as to be irreparable, and which will entail on us an eternal Repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:96673:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> To Speak Little, and Hear O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</head>
               <p>SOme Men have a mighty Fancy to be admir'd in Company; they love to unload all their Store at once, and to lay their Underſtandings naked on the Stage, and but to hear 'em is to tickle their Vanity; ſo that if you be ſilent, and ſeem to devour what they ſay, you will infallibly ſtrike 'em in the Right Vein; for he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſeth Diſcourſe looks on thoſe he ſpeaks to, as Pupils that fit for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: Theſe Talkative Animals are to be ſhunn'd, and left in thoſe Clouds to which they raiſe themſelves, becauſe you will be worn out with their long Twittle Twattle, with their nauſeous Tautologies, and the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96673:40"/>Traſh they are drawn to at laſt to keep on vexing: A Man of Wit, and who knows Men, and who ſubmits to the Pennance to hear what they ſay, ſpeaks ſeldom, but always to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and eſpecially is very reſerv'd in his Determination on nice Subjects, So that concealing his own Sentiment, if Prudence will not permit him to declare it, and Decency doth not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to't, he learns the Reach of others, he can make a Judgment of the Depth of their Underſtanding, and thereby gets clear of thoſe Shelves which boiſterous and over-haſty Talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers run themſelves upon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:96673:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Of Duels.</head>
               <p>'TIS ſtrange, that the horrid Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of fighting Duels has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſo long in <hi>France:</hi> What a Madneſs is it to cut one another's Throats for ſome private Quarrel, and moſt commonly for the verieſt Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles? One cannot without Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment obſerve the Iſſue of theſe inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Practices; he that rages to this heighth, loſes all his Eſtate, is forced to quit his Native Country, to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd for ever from his deareſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, he hazards his Life in the Scuffle, if he overcomes; for what his Adverſary leaves, the Scaffold takes, and to make him completely miſerable, if he falls in the Rencoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his Soul is ſacrifie'd to his Paſſion;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:96673:41"/>but ſome will ſay, 'tis to preſerve his Honor, that he endangers his Perſon at this Rate: A Pretence as wicked as 'tis falſe. How dare Men then where Chriſtianity is Profeſſed ſet this Plea on Foot, that they are repairing Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, at the ſame Minute when they violate the moſt eminent, and moſt indiſpenſable of all other Duties, which is, to obey God? if a Man be perſuaded, that 'tis glorious to execute the Orders of his Prince, can he believe, (if he be not out of his Wits) that it is a Wound to his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation to fullfil the Law of the King of Kings; and for his ſake to ſtifle Reſentments that are often ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and taken up intemperately on petty Scores? But ſetting aſide the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Law, the Monarch, or more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the Hero, which reigns in <hi>France,</hi> very well underſtands in what true Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very conſiſts, yet he reckons 'em both Generous and Brave, who in Compliance with his Edicts can be as impenetrable as a Rock, where others
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:96673:41"/>drew immediately for ſatisfaction; and he either himſelf determines the Compenſation for the Injury, or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits 'em to ſuch Judges, as ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly guard Honor, that the Affront is ſure to be repaid with an adequate Puniſhment; ſo that thoſe who do not take their own Revenge, are ſecure from Inſults, ſince their Prince is Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranty to chaſtize the Attempters; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, all wiſe Men will allow their Conduct the beſt, who can ſmother their Senſe of Wrongs, when God and their King command them to repel the Paſſion: For they know that he who delivers himſelf over to his Choler, and is ſunk into the Extravagance of Revenge, does a thing that taſtes too much of the Brute; but he who keeps the Reins ſtrict over his headſtrong Paſſions, ſhews that he is of the trueſt Mettle, and gives the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Proofs of a great Soul. Is there any farther need to urge more Reaſons to let you into the Senſe of the Crime, and Stupidity of thoſe
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:96673:42"/>Sparks who dare yet revive Duels, that are very near already hiſs'd of the Stage? Let no Man then imitate theſe raſh Fops, but let the ſad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, that ſo many Gallant Men have died with counterfeit Honor in theſe prohibited Quarrels, and the looking back to the danger to which they thereby expoſe themſelves, ſtop the mad Carier of ſuch as are impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly hurried by Boiling Choler, or Red-Hot Revenge, and prevent their being precipitated into thoſe number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Misfortunes, which naturally at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend theſe unjuſtifiable Actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="part">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:96673:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> To give Miniſters of State the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors which are due to 'em.</head>
               <p>TO Crouch meanly before Court-Favourites, and to idolize thoſe who are the Darlings of the People, is too ſervile an Office for Mankind; to deſpiſe them is a peice of Stateli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not to be juſtified; to upbraid them with Miſmanagement is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Fool-hardineſs, ſince thereby a Man may provoke their Reſentment, and expoſe himſelf to all the dire Effects of it, which we have the more Reaſon to fear, becauſe it is in their reach ſo eaſily to cruſh their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. Betwixt theſe vicious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes there is a middle way to ſteer, which is to pay all the Deference and Reſpect which Perſons of Quality can
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:96673:43"/>reaſonably expect to thoſe who are the Diſpenſers of a Prince's Favours, who divide his Cares, and ſweeten the Toils which attend a Crown. 'Tis no leſſening to a Man of Birth, to endeavour to gain their good Will, and not to ſlight the Advantages which he may reap from their Protection, provided that it be not purchaſed by an unmanning of himſelf. But if a Man has receiv'd any Inſtance of their Benefaction, the Laws of Honor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige him to ſhew all the opportune Acknowledgments, where they do not interfere with his firſt Engagements, and do not run counter to an invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable Allegiance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="part">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:96673:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> Of the Love of Pleaſures.</head>
               <p>THere are People in the World who ſo eagerly abandon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their own ſenſual Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that the Conſideration of their Health is no reſtraint to 'em; for whether it be at the Expence of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing or Ruining of it, they will purſue their Debauch. What Title have ſuch to Chriſtianity, who, to gratifie diſorderly Paſſions, will vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late all the Sanctions of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? What Pretence have they to Rationality, that rather than be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridg'd of a Pleaſure, will have it at the coſt of over-leaping all the Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries which Reaſon has preſcrib'd? Is it not a Nick-name to call 'em Men, when by their culpable Extravagance
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:96673:44"/>they depreciate themſelves, and ſink into the Form of Brutes, and by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving leſs Command of themſelves than other Animals, they are in ſome ſort inferior to the vileſt Beaſts, whom Nature hath inſtructed to graſp no more than is neceſſary to their Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. That we may not fall into ſuch Diſorders, let us uſe diſcreetly, and without vehemence, ſuch Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as refin'd Reaſon and the Divine Law have indulg'd us. Let us not be wedded to ſuch flitting and vain ones, as have no Tendency to make us hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py; but let us rather diſpoſe the juſt uſe of 'em to the Glory of God, which is our end, ſo we ſhall entirely ſave three conſiderable Things which Debauchery would wreſt from us; I mean the Purity of our Souls, our Bodily Health, and the uncontroll'd Freedom of our Minds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="part">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:96673:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> To Study Himſelf.</head>
               <p>SElf-Love always turns the Tables on the ſmootheſt Side, every one ſcrews up his own Price, and by a Partiality of Repreſenting ſets a greater Value on himſelf than he has. 'Tis true, what therefore muſt be done to obviate it, there is no ſuch way as to ſtudy our Selves, that is to ſay, to examine ſtrictly, and without any Biaſs; this Enquiry lets us into the Character of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the Diſpoſition of our Mind, and this Scrutiny is of very great uſe to us, it aſſiſts us to all Intents and Purpoſes, to make the beſt of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments, to rectifie our ill Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to ſtrip us of our Vices, and to advance our Virtues. We ſay, ſuch
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:96673:45"/>an one would be a very fine Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and would riſe apace in the World, if he had not one great Fault that he is not ſenſible of, becauſe he never looks at home to ſee what is out of Order there. We ought alſo to reflect with Precaution upon our Actions, but eſpecially on thoſe we have already done, that we may in Futurity ſhew better Steerage; and upon thoſe we are to ſet about, that they may be decently circumſtantiated, and all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful After-claps may be avoided. It coſts dear ſometimes to give way to a Paſſion, or a Crotchet, and an unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Omiſſion, or a mere Maggot inconvenes us afterward with a tedious Repentance; 'tis yet of the higheſt uſe to pry into every Ones Good or Bad Deeds; 'tis good to keep a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of ſome Mens Diſcretion in our View, and where others have been ſhipwrack'd, may well teach us not to ſail on the ſame Coaſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:96673:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> To Converſe with Wiſe Men, of Great Abilities.</head>
               <p>WHen we firſt appear in the World, an Ignorance as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, as 'tis univerſal, lies by us in the Cradle; the Studies which employ us in out Youth, diſſipate in ſome meaſure thoſe Clouds which clog our Underſtanding; afterwards we creep into Knowledge by Cuſtom, and we im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibe a few Notions which are ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to make our Conduct Regular; but the Stock we take in is ſo ſcanty, that it is not adequate to the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of a Man of Quality, who is to move in a higher Orb; how much Speculative Knowledge does he want, beſides what more immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns his Profeſſion, in Morality, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:96673:46"/>and the Politicks? Perhaps he has neither Leiſure nor Wit eno to learn of himſelf what is moſt for his Advantage, and moſt ſuitable to the whole Courſe of his Affairs, what muſt he do then to arrive at Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? He muſt keep company with Men who are moſt eminent in their way; 'tis requiſite to have a judicious Tutor by him, who by long and unwearied Endeavours, has waded into the Depths of Learning; for he has ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated the Traſh of it, and will inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſcatter in his Occaſional Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into his Pupil's Mind all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd and neceſſary Treaſure that every Science locks up. A Great Man with this Management can never fail to ſerve his Country ſucceſsfully, and to gain the Heighth of Applauſe; for his Society with the Virtuoſo's, the Men of Letters, and the moſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated Wits of the Age will ſcarce ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to be unaccompliſh'd in any thing. And as he adorns his Mind with the Flowers he collects from ſuch
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:96673:46"/>as are ſingular in their ſeveral Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, when it beſt ſerves his purpoſe, he appears a perſuaſive Orator, a ſharp Philoſopher, an intelligent Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, an obſerving Stateſman, and an experienced Captain: In a Word, one extremely able to ſurprize the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and takingly to affect the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> To have Variety of Friends.</head>
               <p>AMongſt all the Maxims of true true Policy, this is none of the leaſt uſeful; indeed a Courtier, or one who lives amidſt Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, wants a thouſand different Props to bear him up in the World: good Counſels in the firſt place, how to manage himſelf with Diſcretion, the Advices of a ſincere Friend to rectifie
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:96673:47"/>his Errors, ſome Glittering Metal to defray his neceſſary Expences, Favour to lead him up to Preferment, or to ſecure him in the Continuance of what he has; a Man ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Friendſhip with thoſe who have the Knack to make him Gay when he is ſowr'd, that can ſupport him when he is over-born with Diſgraces, that can remove his Fears when the Load is moſt anxious, he muſt have others to commend his Deſert, and ſtill more to inform him of the Deſigns of his Enemies, to ſide with him againſt their Stratagems, and ſteadily to help him in his own Undertakings. Now 'tis very difficult for one ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to do all this; for tho he had the Will, often it will not fall within the Compaſs of his Power; 'tis therefore neceſſary to have Friends of all ſorts, but ſuch as are branded with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Note of Diſhoneſt. Where one Friend is deficient in Aſſiſtance, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may ſupply it, and that which each in particular is not able to effect, their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:96673:47"/>united Application will eaſily accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh. When I ſay that a Man muſt have different kinds of Friends, I would not be underſtood, as if I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended a ſtrict Cementing of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with abundance, I mean no more than that a Man ought to make it his Buſineſs by fair and obliging Carriage, and above all by his readineſs to do any Civil Office, to gain the Love of thoſe he converſes with, ſo that in any Exigence he may confide in 'em, and not be lurch'd of their Kindneſs when he moſt wants it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Of Great Deſigns.</head>
               <p>GReat Projects are commonly ſo dangerous, and ripen with ſuch Difficulty, there is ſuch a Genius, ſuch a suitable Capacity, ſo much
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:96673:48"/>Prudence and Reſolution required to bring 'em to maturity, that they are only extraordinary Men who can ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in 'em to arrive at that glorious Undauntedneſs, which is eſpecially needful in theſe hazardous Occaſions, and which not only ariſeth from the Strength of Reaſon, but from a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Diſpoſition for it; a Man ought timely to fortifie himſelf with that Armour, that he can ſtand the Shock of Danger, and defie it; that he is not to be frighten'd with any <hi>Hercules</hi> ſtanding in his way; nor diſcourag'd by any Accidents which come athwart him; a Man thus prepared, is ready when he is call'd forth to ſome great Action: For inſtance, to Replace a Crown that has been wreſted from the Head of a Lawful Sovereign, to Reſtore a Diſhonor'd Religion, or to deliver a Groaning Country from its Shackles, he has Vigour eno to conceive, drive on, and execute a Deſign that has ſuch a Latitude of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity. Hiſtory affords us ſignal
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:96673:48"/>Proofs of the Advantage of this Maxim; for it ſhews us, that when Affairs ſeem irretrievable, that Men are diſpirited with Fear, and dwindled into an univerſal Conſternation, one brave Fellow, who is fearleſs, and has a competent Mixture of Prudence with his Courage, may rally a deſponding Army, revive drooping Communities, quicken their ſhrunk and dying Hopes, extirpate State-Locuſts, is able not only to ſettle abſent Peace, and to ſurround a Kingdom with its old Tranquillity, but alſo to augment its Glory, and be once again a Terrour to its Enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> To Affect Nothing.</head>
               <p>AFfectation is ſo far from ſetting off the Luſtre of Beauty, that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates its Charms; and perſons who are otherwiſe handſom, by this auk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:96673:49"/>Air prove always diſagreeable; why ſhould People conſtrain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to pleaſe, Graces are not like Flowers that will thrive in any soil where you would have 'em; 'tis eaſie Nature that gives 'em Being, and in ſpight of that 'tis fruitleſs to expect 'em. As the Eyes of the Mind are more acute and delicate than thoſe of the Body, ſo the leaſt ſhadow of Affectation obſcures and impairs 'em, and nothing agrees with 'em ſo much as what appears with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ornament, eaſie, unforc'd, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artificial; a Man muſt follow his Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, and never depart from it: 'tis this which improves the Pleaſure we meet with in converſing with ingenious Men; ſome have a great ſhare of ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Judgment; others have ſurprizing Strokes of excellent Wit; others there are who invite our Reſpect by the Softneſs of their Addreſs; others ſteal away our Souls by their Lively and Jovial Humour: And if all theſe that are Maſters of ſo many good Qualities, ſhould go out of their
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:96673:49"/>Road to offer at thoſe they are unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, under pretence that they would agree better with 'em, they would go a great way in making themſelves ridiculous; let therefore every one keep the Character which ſuits him, with aſſurance, that he will ceaſe to pleaſe that very moment he quits it, to uſurp another which he does not underſtand; not that it is improper to hide any Deformities in Body or Mind; and if it be poſſible to make 'em paſſable, at leaſt, thoſe of the Mind, but no Man ſhould go in Queſt of artificial Set-offs, which, when they are obtain'd, will ſtill look unnatural, ſince 'tis certain, that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body is ſo much the leſs lovely, the more pains they take to appear ſo. This holds equally in Virtues, where Affectation in 'em deſtroys all their Charms, and blaſts the whole Merit they pretend to.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="part">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:96673:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> To know what will take with the Age.</head>
               <p>THO Men in all Times agree in many Things, yet they widely differ in many others; there is a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Difference betwixt ours, and our Anceſtors Way of Living. If any one will give himſelf the Trouble to make the Compariſon, we may ſee an old Courtier, that was a Complete Maſter in the Art of treading Court-Mazes, who now would be much perplex'd to know how to demean himſelf; for 'tis with Courts under divers Reigns, as 'tis in Comedies, Love and Ambition ſit out the great Characters of the Stage, yet the Intrigues of both are manag'd with great Variety; the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes and the Milk-ſops do not ſight and whine the ſame way; ſo Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:96673:50"/>Love, and other Paſſions haunt Courts ſtill, but they are not now to be manag'd the ſame way they were heretofore: Beſides as the People that are now in that Labyrinth are more ſly and ſubtle, new Tricks muſt be try'd to fathom 'em; we muſt ſtudy the Cuſtoms, the Ways, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſition of our Age, not thereby to gratifie our guilty Affections, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to take ſpecial Care of our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, that they may know how to ſhape themſelves to the preſent Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of Things, to unravel the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Clues which lead the Perſons we have to do with; and laſtly, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover which are the neareſt Ways to gain every Bodies Favour, and ſo get the Point we are deſirous to obtain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="part">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:96673:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> To know how to be well Employed when we are alone.</head>
               <p>THE Averſion which Men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain for Solitude, is moſt commonly an Indication either of the Narrowneſs of the Underſtanding, or of deprav'd Manners, and yet there are whole Shoals in the World which are tir'd downright with the privacy of one half hour; their Time lies upon their Hands, they are diſquieted, and fretting, and even drown'd in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, being a Burthen to themſelves; but Men who are well weighed, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of every Minute of their. Time to Advantage, and are never buſie to more purpoſe, than when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; 'tis then they form the Schemes which do 'em moſt good; they ſcan with Niceneſs the Particulars they are
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:96673:51"/>to ſet about; they pitch upon the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt way to ſerve their Friends, and to defend 'em from the Attacks of their Enemies, to crown their Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, commendably to diſcharge their Duties. To conclude, 'tis then that they beſtow a thouſand needful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on their own Conduct, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mens; and if there be any over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plus time, they make uſe of it to read Books, which inſtruct and divert at the ſame moment; or they faſten upon ſome ingenious and noble Art, or they ſingle out that Science they delight in, and poliſh it; Experience daily acquaints us what a Fund of Life we provide, when we wiſely diſpoſe of our vacant Hours; for my part, I do aſſure you, as the Practice of this Maxim highly vindicates our Conduct, ſo 'tis a main Pillar on which our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs does relie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="part">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:96673:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> Not to Judge of Actions by the Event.</head>
               <p>FOrtune is ſo us'd to play the Jilt, that ſhe has often baffled the beſt concerted Deſigns, but then ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pillage us of the Glory of having taken prudential Methods to ſucceed; 'tis eno' for an able Man, that he has o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nothing which might reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly conduce to bring his Enterprize to a good Iſſue; and then a lucky Hit, or a Miſcarriage ſhould neither cramp nor amplifie that Commendation which he deſerves. I confeſs the Humour of the World runs violently the other way; for if a Man's Sails be fill'd with Succeſs, then he ſhall be vogu'd for a Man of Conduct; but if he is once ſtranded by a Diſappointment, he ſhall never get off the Ignominy: They, whoſe Reach is ſo ſhallow that it ſtrikes no farther than the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:96673:52"/>of Things, are led away by the bare Impreſſions of Senſe; but Men of correct Judgments are not thus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd on, being taught by Experience, that Accidents often break the juſteſt Meaſures; they can diſtinguiſh nicely what ſhare uncertain Fortune has in an Action, and where it is that Prudence gave Birth, and Direction to it: Some Men will hunt after Reputation in the ready Road to loſe it, they will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit intolerable Blunders in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance, and yet by Chance-Medley, get thro' 'em, when at the ſame time time others ſhall lay as hopeful Schemes as if they were overcharged with Wiſdom, and yet can borrow no Succeſs to recommend 'em. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs 'tis ten to one, if he, who keeps clear of Rocks, and gets ſafe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Port, be not only applauded, but advanc'd, tho it was the moſt unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed thing to run into the Mouth of ſo much danger; but let a Man have never ſo much perſonal Worth, that it riſes very near Veneration, and ſends
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:96673:53"/>abroad but one abortive Iſſue of his Brain, the ill-natur'd World preſently ſnatches up Pretenſions of Raſhneſs, or Neglect, whereby to worry and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour his Credit. So partial are the moſt of Men, as to approve that which ought to be condemn'd, and where they ſhould be eminently favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, there to lay the moſt frowning Sentence, yet, let not any ill-ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cenſure be big eno' to damp our Courage, but rather, when we recur to the Teſtimony of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and in Conjunction with this, find, that thoſe who do not run with a Biaſs, put an equitable Conſtruction on our Actions, and beyond all this, that there is an indiſpenſable Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion due to the Will of God, who or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or permits all that befalls us; let us rally amidſt all Oppreſſion, ſmile under the Cloud, and be more than Conquerors over an inhoſpitable Race of Wou'd-be-Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="part">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:96673:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> What a Man is to do for his Friend.</head>
               <p>AS there is no Man conſummate in every Point, ſo doubtleſs a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is brought to this Dilemma, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to quit all Friendſhip, or to bear with the Defects of his Friends, but perhaps it may be ſtarted, whether we are bound in all Emergencies to aſſiſt thoſe whom we are endeared to? This Queſtion has been decided by what has been ſaid under the Head, <hi>Of the Choice of a Friend;</hi> and indeed, if two Friends do not wear Masks, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Deſcription I have given of 'em, they will never ask any thing of one another which is not juſt, and ſo conſequently muſt be granted on both ſides; but if one of, 'em proves a ſhrouded Friend, and would require any thing of the other, which has a direct Repugnancy to his Duty, he has
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:96673:54"/>all the Reaſon imaginable to expect a Refuſal. Such an Offer is an Act of Hoſtility, and Treachery is ſeen thro' the Cloak of Kindneſs; here is no Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen of Love, but rather the viſible Improbity which ariſeth from Hatred, that can be willing to drive a Friend upon the Precipice of Ill; theſe have a Deſign to break in upon our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: but there are other fantaſtical ſort of Friends, who believe a Man oblig'd by the Seal of Friendſhip to be always of their Opinion, and upon this falſe Principle take pet, if you oppoſe their Impertinence; People of this Temper do but ape Friends; yet they ought to be acquainted, that ſuch a blind Complaiſance is unreaſonable; and if that will not ſatisfie, I conceive it the beſt way to retire inſenſibly from ſuch Company, and to let Friendſhip dwindle into bare good Manners. But if a Man chance to live in ſuch a bleſt Angle of the World, as to find a wiſe and virtuous Friend, we ought never to be uncompliant in his Service, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:96673:54"/>his Requeſts, and if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to ſtep forward, and anticipate his Deſires, there is no more to be done; but that every one ſpares the Importuning of his Friends, when he finds the Application is their Torment, and never overload 'em with the worſt part of his Humour; for nothing more diſcoves an Ignorance of the Rules of Friendſhip; no powerful Temptation can engage an Honeſt Man to make his Friend uneaſie, but he will take a thouſand Steps to remove all the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles of his Happineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIV.</hi> Of a Gay Humour, and the Uſe of Jesting.</head>
               <p>IF to be Merry and wiſe can ſtand together, at leaſt commonly they are oppoſite to one another, the firſt ſhews a volatile Inclination is unfit for great Exploits; but the other on
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:96673:55"/>the contrary diſcovers a profound Underſtanding, which deſpiſing Trifles ſets upon what is ſolid, and is addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to nothing but what is of moment; beſides, the Cuſtom of Joking does by no Means, in my Opinion, ſuit a Man of Quality; 'tis the Buſineſs of common People to make ſport for Company; if any thing is well ſaid, 'tis applauded; if they prate fooliſhly, they are laugh'd at; and what ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies all this? But ſuch as are diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by their Birth, or their Figure in the World, ſink their Character much when they turn Drolls, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to the Deriſion of their Hearers; 'tis too undervaluing an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to arrive at the knack to make all others laugh, unleſs it be by chance, and without any labour'd Deſign, to ſay a ſine thing; yet I am not ſo Stoical, that I would have Perſons of Quality entertain one another in the Saturnine Way; let 'em rally, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſſenſively; let the Raillery be noble and fine, ſuch as may divert the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:96673:55"/>with Strokes of Wit, interlarded with Mirth and Vivacity, but let theſe witty Jeſts be always becoming the Dignity of the Speaker, let 'em ſtrike home, but clean, and ſuch as may make no Inroads upon Civility and good Breeding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> To Neglect Nothing.</head>
               <p>AS Profitable as this Maxim would be in human Life, yet 'tis not put in Execution with any great Care. A young Man eſpecially, who does not love to be contradicted, takes but little pains to obſerve it, becauſe it would put him to the Expence of ſome Reflections upon his Conduct, and the Poſtute of his Affairs; but he does not mind all this while, that the Omiſſion of a Duty which he thinks unneceſſary, may defeat him of that Poſt he is reaching to obtain. This happen'd to <hi>Mr.</hi>— he loſt an Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:96673:56"/>of Riſing, for want of a Pat Viſit to the Duke of — that was to be diſcourſed about a great Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: one can't be too nice, or too careful in the Tranſacting a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Matter. A wiſe Man that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon Buſineſs, endeavours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move any Impediment that may croſs it, or be a Block in the way of his Advancement; for he foreſees that a little Obſtacle unremov'd, either thro' Inconſiderateneſs , or becauſe 'tis ſlighted, ſometimes balks a good De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and prevents its coming to a good Iſſue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Of the Uſe is to be made of Great Mens Favours.</head>
               <p>DIſgrac'd Courtiers may ſay what they will, that their Fall is by the undermining of their Enemies, or the Maggoty Turn of Fortune's
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:96673:56"/>Wheel; but if it be ſeverely examin'd, their Diſgrace generally ariſeth from their own ill Conduct, they abuſe the Credit, Princes and their Patrons give 'em; and when they have done ſo, how unreaſonable is it for 'em to imagine they ſhould not be under a Declenſion? Favour in it ſelf is very tickliſh, and there are a thouſand Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhers lie at catch to ſeize it; whence it follows, that to preſerve it, Men muſt govern themſelves with Care, and make uſe of it prudently, and with much Precaution; if you will be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of this Treaſure, and not let it ſlip out of your Hands, purſue this following Advice: Be civil, honorable, and modeſt; for Haughtineſs and a lofty Humour, will draw upon you Clouds of Hatred, and Black Envy, whereas Genteelneſs and fair Carriage will imprint a Belief that you deſerve your Poſt. In the next place never beg any thing for your ſelf, or at leaſt very rarely, if a Prince or a Great Man underſtands, that your Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:96673:57"/>to his Service is ſincere, and diſintereſted, his Largeſſes will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand with your Intreaties, then, be ſure you never move for an unjuſt thing; Fourthly, do not ſtake down your own Credit, but for perſons who have a large Stock of it themſelves, and that too but ſeldom: In the fifth place, let your Requeſts be always well tim'd, and tender'd with great Modeſty and Reſpectfulneſs. Laſtly, be not lame in acknowledging the Bounty you reap, and publiſh to the World by your redoubled Zeal for your Maſtet's Service, that you are not inſenſible of the Value of your Benefactor. 'Tis thus you are to manage the Favour of of Great Men, and by ſuch a Method you will aſſuredly oblige 'em to retain the Affection for you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:96673:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Of Superfluity and Neatneſs.</head>
               <p>TO be Neat, is not only advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous, but one may even vouch for its Neceſſity; for beſides that it contributes to our Health, it goes a great Way in mending our Decorum in the World, ſo that a Genteel Man muſt by no means neglect himſelf; yet there is a great deal of Difference betwixt being cleanly, and being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice; every one in this matter is to live in a due Compaſs, and to have Reſpect to his Age, and his Quality: In reference to another ſort of Neatneſs which conſiſts in the way of Dreſſing, I hold it to be innocent, and as to that we may follow the Mode; but to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly expenſive in Cloaths, in Furniture, in Buildings, in Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in Equipage, to value himſelf for eclipſing others in any of theſe,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:96673:58"/>and even to Rival the Magnificence Princes, is an Effect of Pride, and an Affectation unbecoming a wiſe Man. They that take ſuch Pains to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by things that ſcarce deſerve our Thought, give great ground to believe, that being conſcious of a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency of Merit, they would dazle their Admirers with outward Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. When a Man comes once to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what true Glory is, and to find himſelf capable to acquire it, he contemns that Luxury which ſo much puts upon the Brutal Herd of Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> To have as few Enemies as you can.</head>
               <p>YOU cannot beat it into ſome Mens Heads, that there is any reaſon to fear the Underling World, which they ſcorn, and abuſe on all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ons; ſay they, we ſtand on ſuch high Ground, that their Arrows, tho
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:96673:58"/>levell'd at us, can do us no Miſchief ('tis as whimſical as the Giants At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to dethrone <hi>Jupiter</hi>) but they are much in the wrong; for Hatred and the ſweet Deſire of Revenge are ſuch ingenious Paſſions, they are ſo wakeful to gain their Ends, that they will ſall upon ſuch Methods as you could never have imagin'd they would purſue, Men of the vileſt Condition having nothing of their own to ſave, are eaſily whetted to have at all of other Mens, and as inconſiderable as we think 'em, 'tis dangerous to drive 'em to extremity. Now if a Set of Enemies beneath us have ſo much Power ſometimes to plague us, what ſhall become of us, if we provoke the Malice of our Equals, which are in better Circumſtances to annoy us, or by inflaming our Superiors, blow up that Fire which is nor to he quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by our own entire Ruine? It follows from hence, that we are to diſoblige no Body, but to behave our ſelves with ſuch Circumſpection, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:96673:59"/>diſcreet Management towards all, that we may leave every Body vying who ſhall have the beſt Opinion of us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Not to be Diſcourag'd.</head>
               <p>'TIS the peculiar of a narrow Soul to have his Courage flatten'd at the approach of the leaſt Difficulty; a Man of Reſolution, and who truly bears his Maker's Image, is aſtoniſh'd at nothing, but finds a Cure for every Ill; he ſtands brave, where others ſneak, where others ſtumble, and are born down with fear, he ſtands his Ground, and ſnatches an Occaſion from hence to look above danger, and to triumph where others fell; 'tis then that by a more vigorous purſuit he doubles his Pace, and preſſing on with extraordinary Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, he often breaks thro' every thing that ſtands in his way: Great Men never ſhew more Courage, than when they are at the very Brink of Deſpair, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:96673:59"/>Experience has inform'd 'em that a little Matter has chang'd a whole Scene of Affairs, or at leaſt, that a ſeaſonable Shew of Boldneſs, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous puſhing, has not only extrica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves out of Danger, but ſtruck Terror in their Enemies; this ſtout Reſiſtance in terrible Shocks, tho it ſhould meet with ill Succeſs, would yet mightily befriend the Character of the Commanders, and therefore 'tis chiefly neceſſary for Kings and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of an Army; for if <hi>they</hi> be ſtunn'd, and do but ſeem ſtagger'd with any frightful Apprehenſion, the main Body of the Soldiers immediately eye it, and will not ſtay to ſtare Death in the Face, but become a cheap Prey to the willing Conqueror.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> Of Pride.</head>
               <p>WHY ſhould we value our ſelves ſo much upon our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and give our ſelves the Preference
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:96673:60"/>to ſo many others, who perhaps have more worth concentred in 'em than we have; are not our Bodies deriv'd from the ſame Original, and our Souls the bright Product of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor? whatſoever Advantages we are endebted for, either to Nature, or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; 'tis a great Inſtance of our Weakneſs, it they make us more high-ſpirited; for theſe are but a poor Enjoyment at the beſt, but yet they are preſently weighed down, if we put 'em in the Scale with the Privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Heaven, to which our Faith prompts us to aſpire; they often ſlee away in ſpight of all our jealous Care to retain 'em, and a Man of ſound Underſtanding ſlights 'em, becauſe by being Maſter of 'em he does not find that he is veſted in any ſolid Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he looks after; and altho he could poſſeſs 'em without Diſlike, or preſerve 'em without Diſturbance, the Thread of Life is ſo ſuddenly cut off, that he muſt be proud of a very little matter, who will be puff'd up with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:96673:60"/>the Conceit of all theſe Advantages, which in a few fleeting Hours he muſt ſurrender; ſooner or later Death ſeizes on 'em, it ſtrips us (as I may ſay) of our glittering, but borrow'd Dreſs, and by that inſtructs us, that when we have div'd into the greateſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Men, they are all equally miſerable; and there is no Fence againſt that Claim. I confeſs ſometimes we do a thing that a Commendation does not ſeem to be thrown away upon it; but then conſider that ſelf-love is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ever the Motive that ſpurs us on to Action, we have more reaſon to mortifie our Pride in doing it, than to aſſume any Vain-Glory for the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance. Perſons, whoſe Piety is the moſt reſin'd, and unmix'd, who only, it ſeems, ſhould have ſome Right to value themſelves more than others, are remov'd at the greateſt Diſtance from Pride, being perſuaded not only that it is the capital Enemy of all Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and that it poiſons their very Fountain; but that beſides 'tis always
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:96673:61"/>ill grounded. To conclude, this Vico is unjuſt, becauſe it makes a Man u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp that Glory to himſelf, which in Propriety of Speech belongs only to God; 'tis odious, becauſe it induceth us to deſpiſe every Body; and to ſum up all in ſhort, it ſtands in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect oppoſition to the true Humility, for which Saints are Glorified, and which influencerh us to love God, and and our Neighbour to the bell purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> To Regulate a Man's Expences.</head>
               <p>'TIS abſolutely neceſſary for him that will carry his Figure high in the World, to proportion his Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out to his Revenue. How are they who ſquainter away their Eſtates diſregarded, and who are always be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by their Creditors? He is mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken that would, be cry'd up for a
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:96673:61"/>bountiful Man that way, and who thinks to riſe at Court by being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe; the Prince and his Miniſters make a natural Judgment preſently, that he who cannot improve his own fortune, and Regulate his Domeſtick Affairs, is very uncapable to be the Guardian of a State, to command an Army, or to take the beſt Courſe to eſtabliſh the Peace of Provinces; whence we ſee daily, that they who ſwell their Out-lets much beyond their coming in, to cheriſh ſome prevailing Paſſion, as Hunting, Luxury, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches and Play, never get any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Employment; ſo that let their Parts be never ſo good, they ſignifie nothing to 'em, becauſe they have no Opportunity to take off their ruſt. Covetouſneſs is abominable, without doubt, there is no Vice that more points out a mean-ſpirited Man than that; but if Prodigality is leſs criminal in the beginning, its Sting is more to be dreaded afterwards; there are nevertheless ſome peculiar
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:96673:62"/>Occaſions, where to he laviſh is commendable, as when 'tis for the ſake of Religion, for Publick Good, or the eminent Service of a Friend; if theſe be excepted, keep always to a wiſe good Husbandry, and retrench all unneceſſary Expences; this is the true way to be continually ſupply'd with what is neceſſary, to live hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in his Station, and for a Man to be altogether Independent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> To know how to Chuſe his Company.</head>
               <p>MOST Men have an over-ween<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Opinion of themſelves, are conceited of their Nobility, their Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur, their Knowledge, their Wit, and their other natural and acquir'd Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; they are commonly humourſome, hot ſtubborn, deceitful, full of Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wedded to Intereſt, and Envy, and the like. I confeſs theſe falſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:96673:62"/>Steps ſeldom meet together, but few perſons can boaſt of their Exemption from all o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m: in a word, Vice is ſo rampant, and Virtue ſo much out of Countenance, that a Man never ſo inclin'd to be ſociable, durſt not mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his Acquaintance; yet ſince we cannot live alone, or without ſome friendly Entercourſe, unleſs we bid adieu to the World all at once; A Man is oblig'd, for the Eaſe of his own Life, to chuſe a ſmall number of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Perſons, and to hold a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with 'em, where Piety. mutual Confidence, Sincerity, good Breeding, and if it be poſſible, Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may make one glorious Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; the Pleaſure and Conveniency of ſuch Company is inexpreſſible; for there, as we unbend our Cares, we are recreated after a Fatigue; when Diſgraces ſtab us, here we are infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly heai'd, that's the proper place to paſs an Act of Oblivion on all our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts; 'tis there we fill the Magazine of our Minds with a thouſand good
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:96673:63"/>Things, which we draw out for the ſeveral Occaſions of our Lives; to finiſh all, this is the way to make time ſlide pleaſantly, and with the greateſt Stroke of Advantage to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> Of ſharp Raillery, and Villifying.</head>
               <p>THere is no ſuch cruel Diverſion as ſome People take in bitter Jeſts; what a Stock of Malice muſt they have to ſet up with, who take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Satisfaction in beſpattering with this ſort of Drollery the Underſtanding of thoſe they fall upon, and hug them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the Thought that they have run others to a Stand; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Religion, Civility and Prudence oblige us to baniſh from our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation all venemous Diſcourſes, which are not only ill in themſelves, but may have alſo very miſchievous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences attend 'em; let Detraction be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:96673:63"/>ſhut out of all Company; for at the beſt 'tis perfidious to ſpeak ill of our Friends, 'tis downright Malice to ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniate them who are indifferent to us, and 'tis errant Cowardlineſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile our Enemies; beſides that diſcreet, Men give very little Credit to Words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t have ſo much of the Wormwood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh in 'em; thoſe who feel the Point <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is Satyr, make him pay very dear <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the fine Things he ſaid only to recreate the Gueſts: He that is foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth'd may accidentally pleaſe, but every Body is ſhy of him; every one apprehends him his particular Enemy, because 'tis well known, Obloquy ſpares no Body, and that the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its blemiſh'd Virtue is not ſhelter'd from its Darts. Reputation coſts ſo much in the purchaſe, that 'tis perfect Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to have but an Inclination to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory it, or upon any pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever to ruine a Work for whoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition ſo much Sweat and Pains has been expended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="part">
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:96673:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIV.</hi> Of Sincerity.</head>
               <p>THIS Virtue is ſo eſſential to Perſons of Quality, and this Age is ſo little acquainted with, that it will not be Labour thrown away to ſet down in this place ſome Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of it; for I can't Imagine, that unleſs a Man's Mind be corrupted by the falſe Maxims now in Vogue, he can know it, and not be ſtruck with admiration of it at the ſame time; we ſay therefore that a ſincere Man never makes uſe of Diſguiſes, or Cheating to obtain his Ends, he cannot endure any ambiguous and equivocal Terms, which Sharpers make uſe of to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize thoſe who act freely: he never promiſeth more than he will perform, and he religiouſly obſerves his Word when he hath once engag'd it; if he finds that more is expected from him
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:96673:64"/>than he can agree to, he explains his Intentions, that he may entertain no Body with vain Hopes, he doth not publiſh every Truth he knows, nor diſcloſe all his Thoughts, becauſe very often Charity and Prudence do forbid it; but when theſe licenſe him to ſpeak, he plainly tells his Mind, and cloaks the Truth of nothing which concerns his friends, tho they are kept in the dark for every thing beſides; his Virtue ſhines ſo much the brighter, the leſs pains he takes to publiſh it; and as he hates all Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation, his way is infinitely enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, becauſe 'tis plain, and natural; 'tis not that he yields himſelf up to he cheated, he takes the beſt Method to keep clean of the Snares that are laid for him; but 'tis always by neceſſary Conſiderations, without ſhewing the leaſt ſuſpicion; his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Candor join'd to his great Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, gains him every Bodies Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and every Body grows proud to be acquainted with a Man of this
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:96673:65"/>Character. Such Plain Dealing is rare without doubt, and eſpecially at Court. Yet I have ſeen Maſters of this ſine Quality to that Degree, that it would be impoſſible for you to know 'em, without having, I will not ſay, not only an Eſteem, but even a Veneration for 'em. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, Diſſimulation, which has more Artifice, and Craft, than Diſcretion, and true Policy, does a Man as much harm that would ſettle, and advance his Reputation in the World, as the Plain-Dealing, I have ſpoke of, does him good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> Of Reconciliations.</head>
               <p>THey who ſtubbornly refuſe to be reconcil'd to their Adverſaries, diſcover but very little Religion, and give us to underſtand, that their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per borders upon that of Wild Beaſts,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:96673:65"/>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſeleſs Fury is never ſatiated, till they have torn in peices one of their own Species that was the Object of it; Hatred ſeldom lodges in a Brave Mind, and if it ever happens that it does, it never robs it of ſome lucky Seaſons, which eaſily induce it to a reaſonable Accommodation; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs I muſt confeſs, 'tis very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to pardon an Aſſaſſin, or one who violates our Honour; but when this is done, the greater our Struggle is to ſmother our Reſentment, the more Glory waits upon our Victory; and a Man in nothing more demonſtrates the Largeneſs of his Soul. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People can't carry up their Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſo high; indeed there are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who have ſuch an abſolute Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over their Paſſions, that they can forget the Wrongs are done 'em, and be reconciled in good earneſt; but there are others who are only Friends outwardly, and out of Policy; they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to be branded with Impiety if they don't do it. or they dare not diſoblige
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:96673:66"/>their Friends, who preſs 'em to agree, and yet the Serpent is as dangerous as before, and waits only an Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to exert its Sting; to have nothing to do with ſuch People, the beſt way would be to offend no Body; but if the Hoſtility is begun, and that we are convinc'd, that thoſe we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd are not really good Friends with us, let us behave our ſelves towards 'em with double Civility; let us take off the Edge of their Hatred, by the Aſſiduity of our Service, let us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt 'em without letting 'em know ſo much; let us be as jealous of 'em, as of Enemies who will feize upon every Occaſion to do us harm if they can come at it? For our parts, let us aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our Sincerity, let us ſet all things to Rights like Honeſt Men, and fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhut up all Differences without cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticizing on Formalities. Mean Souls are inſupportable in this point, 'tis difficult to compound any thing with ſuch parties, they are never content, till they have adjuſted with the utmoſt
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:96673:66"/>Exactneſs, the place, the time, the very Words that muſt be ſpoke, and even to the minuteſt Steps which each ſide muſt purſue in ſuch Affairs; but deſerving Men who know in what true Honor conſiſts, never fall into this Fault, but compose Quarrels in a more noble Faſhion, where the Sparks of Generoſity rekindle expiring Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> Not to be Fickle.</head>
               <p>WHen once we have ſet about a Buſineſs, let us drive it up to the Hilts, and not ſuffer our ſelves to be dazl'd by the Splendour of any ſhining Advantage, which is ſpread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Eyes to impoſe on us, a ſubtle Competitor who ſees us juſt ready to graſp the place we aim at, and that he would alſo ſhap for himſelf, endeavours to draw us off from the Chace, either
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:96673:67"/>by miſrepreſenting it, to give us a Diſreliſh of it, or by putting us upon engaging a Friend to deal the Cards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for a more conſiderable Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for us. Let us not be noos'd in this Snare, but ever prefer an Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage in poſſeſſion, tho inconſiderable, to a tranſcendent Seat, but in the Clouds. Let us alſo forbear imitating thoſe perſons, who by a peculiar Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity throw Obſtacles in the way of their own riſing, and are the only Men who obſtruct the Progreſs of their Fortune, being inconſtant in their Projects, they have no ſooner em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd one ſide, or adher'd to one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but as their Maggot bites, they ſally out to another; no Man can do any Feats in the World by ſuch fantaſtical Conduct: And after all theſe Shiftings and doublings the Spark is not a whit the more ſatisfy'd, or in a higher Poſt than he was the firſt Day. A Man muſt fix ſome time or other, and when he has taken upon him ſuch a Courſe of Life, he is to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:96673:67"/>ſtick by it, and labour to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as accompliſh'd, and happy in it as is poſſible; this does not exclud c a Man neither, who has unluckily made a bad Choice at firſt, from changing his Condition or Employment; but a wiſe Man will never make that ſtep without conſidering all the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences which may attend it; and without being very ſure, not only that nothing will be loſt by the Change, but alſo that there is ſomething va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable to be got by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> The Character of a Cowardly, and Faint-hearted Man.</head>
               <p>ONE Coward, who cunningly conceals his Hatred, is more to be fear'd than two declared Enemies; for as he never dares attack a perſon bare-fac'd, ſo be has Recourſe to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:96673:68"/>Treachery and Artifice; and that which makes his ſhot the more mortal, is, becauſe as they are unexpected, we know not what Coaſt to guard to prevent 'em. Fear, which makes him apprehend Danger where there is none, perſuades him at the ſame time to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, and engageth him to take ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Precautions againſt Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Ills; his Fear ariſeth from the Weakneſs of his Mind, which makes him ſuſpicious, and to live in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Diffidence; ſo that he looks upon moſt Men as his Enemies, tho for the moſt part they don't think of him. He has but few Friends, or rather he has none at all; for being always jealous of being deceived, he ſticks to no Body, and is loth to do a Civil Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, for fear he ſhould hazatd ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the means; he is ſo unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageable in Buſineſs, that it would be impoſſible to ſettle any thing with him, if you do not give him all ſort of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity; which ſtill he takes in ſuch a manner, as if it grated and bore hard
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:96673:68"/>upon him to take up with ſuch an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient. Theſe are ſome of the ill Effects that Cowardlineſs and Fear peſter the World with; whence 'tis eaſie to conceive how neceſſary it is to ſhun the Converſation of ſuch dwarf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Souls, that being born with theſe Clogs, have neglected to manumiſe 'em by the Succours of Reaſon, and the Principles of unerring Virtue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVIII.</hi> Of Gratitude.</head>
               <p>THE moſt ſtigmatiz'd Man that ever liv'd, can't avoid having a ſecret Veneration for Honeſt Men, and to admire in 'em what he will not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe himſelf, whence it proceeds, that Men who are ſignally grateful, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd by all the World, even by the ungrateful; ſo that Gratitude of it ſelf is a natural Duty, and cones<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently indiſpenſable; a good Mind
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:96673:69"/>ſenſibly feels the Force of this Law of Nature; and if there be any Body who knows truly to value a good Turn, 'tis always a Noble and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Soul; ſpare therefore nothing in acknowledging the good Offices Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors have done for you; and if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Opportunity, or the Power of doing it be wanting, at leaſt, give all the Demonſtration you can, that you are deſirous to do it. Altho Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullness were none of our Duty, 'tis always fraught with Advantages; for he that has had the Skill duly to acknowledge the firſt Favours he has receiv'd, infallibly invites others to the old Heap: 'tis true, there are ſome, that for the ſake of a ſmall Courteſie which they have done you, would <hi>double tax</hi> you for Repayment. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho this is unreaſonable, yet Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity ought to engage you in ſuch a Caſe to gratifie the Requeſts of thoſe who have firſt oblig'd you, animated by this fine Maxim, that in the Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Gratitude a Man cannot go
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:96673:69"/>too far. If you have oblig'd others, never put 'em in mind of it, nor fancy that they are altogether indebted to you, if you can ſhun, it require nothing of 'em that owe you Obligations; but if the ill poſture of your Affairs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitates you to deſire a Kindneſs of 'em, do't with ſo much Modeſty and Reſervedneſs, that it may ſeem you have forgot the Services you have done for 'em. I ſhall not here take upon me to rail againſt Ingratitude, every one knows, that 'tis as odious, as its contrary is lovely, and that the ungrateful have always paſs'd for Men abandon'd of Honor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> To Avoid Conteſts.</head>
               <p>NO Man ought to plunge himſelf into Diſputes, but to bring Truth aſhore with him, whether it be to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his own Itch, or that he would,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:96673:70"/>after finding it, impart to others his own Diſcovery, now a Truth ſquabbl'd for, is either indifferent in it ſelf, or contrary to the Inclinations of thoſe we converſe with, or oppoſite to their Prejudices; if this Truth he indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, why ſuch a Clutter about it? Why do we keep ſo much ado to no purpoſe to make it ſink into their Heads? Is it not more opportune to ſhew 'em a reaſonable Complaiſance, than to provoke 'em by thwarting, which can no ways be ſerviceable: If I would have another ſwallow a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable Truth, I muſt guild it, or at leaſt put a better Colour upon it, and to ſucceed in it, Civility and Sweetneſs of Addreſs muſt by no means be wanting; for eager Claſhing, and the Heat of Deſputation undoes all. A Heart maybe nicked to ſurrender, but muſt not be taken by ſtorm. Above all Places you muſt never enter there by the Breach. To conclude, if the Truth in queſtion runs counter to their Prejudices, the only way to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:96673:70"/>ceive 'em, is not to reject their Opinion with Contempt, and to dreſs up the Authors in Fools Coats, nor to ſpeak huffingly, and with a deciſive Air, this makes him you would convince revolt farther from you, and hinders him from embracing rational Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Thoſe whom we would drive from their Prejudices, we muſt attack ſlily, and by the help of deep Reaſon demonſtrate to 'em how groundleſs they are; and then void of Paſſion, and with a good ſhare of Modeſty, a Man may go near the clinching of a contrary Sentiment. 'Tis thus, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Men manage Diſputes; and ſo Learned Branglings have ſome Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and Pleaſure in 'em. If we meet with ſome reſtleſs Tempers, that are ſtill vex'd, and upon the Fret, 'tis in vain to ſtruggle with 'em, it will only ſowr 'em the more: In ſuch a Caſe a Man has no more to do, but to hug that Truth he is Maſter of, and to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Obſtinacy of thoſe who will ſhut their Eyes againſt the cleareſt Conviction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="part">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:96673:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>L.</hi> To be Regular in his Conduct.</head>
               <p>HE that would be Regular in his Conduct, and live ſuitably to the Rules of Decency, ought to treat all Men according to their Quality, but without any Encroachments on Civility. Reſpect he muſt pay to his Superiors, Allegiance to his Lawful Maſters, Fairneſs of Carriage to his Equals, and a favourable Reception to his Inferiors; for Men that are under Vaſſalage, if they diſcharge their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations with Fidelity, ought to be treated ſoftly, and with Generoſity; but if they forfeit their Tyes, Severity is neceſſary to chaſtiſe 'em. But 'tis not eno' to give Admonition of Duty where 'tis wanting, and to correct thoſe who undervalue the Counſel, unleſs he who preſcribeſ it, makes his own Actions bear the Teſt of the moſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:96673:71"/>Obſerver; for would it be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to condemn and puniſh with Severity, in another, thoſe Faults which a precedent Practice has at leaſt countenanc'd, if not giv'n Licenſe to. Nothing is ſo moving to promote Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, in the World, as the unutterable Force of a good Example. Every one is oblig'd to ſcatter this Light for his Neighbour, but it ſticks cloſer to Princes, and Great Men, becauſe as every Body is proud to imitate 'em, either Virtue flouriſhes, or Vice, as they ſee their Degeneracy, or Probity, in the perpetual Circle of an active Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LI.</hi> How one may make a Judgment of Men.</head>
               <p>IF it muſt be a fine Operator, who can handſomely take in peices a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Body, he muſt certainly be a
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:96673:72"/>great Maſter, who is capable to diſſect the Mind, and anatomize the Heart, by which, I mean the natural Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of it. Self-Love hides it ſelf ſo artfully, that he muſt be very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicacious, that can take a View of it thro' the Appearances of Virtue, where it takes Covert; 'tis therefore neceſſary to watch it ſtrictly, if you would detect the Legerdemain; in publick it cheats the niceſt Inquiſition, ſo that there is no Judgment to be made of a Man by what he acts on the open Stage; as he ſees himſelf ey'd, he puts his Affections on the Tenters, and you can have no true Picture of the real Man, eſpecially in Actions of Note, where every Body labours to purchaſe Reputation, and therefore induſtriouſly conceals any Peccadillo that might cauſe a Flaw in his Title to't. 'Tis in the Tiring-Room that we muſt weigh him, whoſe Manners we would unravel, and whoſe Inclinations we would ſcan; then his Mind is unbent, he ſwims
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:96673:72"/>with the Current of his Senſes, and whatſoever is good or ill in him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears above board; and yet this is not eno' to judge of his Deſert, let us obſerve in the firſt place, if he be ſway'd by Intereſt; for if he be not, that's a Demonſtration that his Soul is above the common Level. Let us examine in the next place, if he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges well the Obligations of his Station, and if we find he does, 'tis a plain Indication of a ſolid Wit; but if we perceive, that he can proſtrate himſelf before the Idol of Intereſt, that he neglects to do the Duty of his Calling, let him have never ſo many other good Qualities, he deſerves to be blotted out of our Roll of Friends, and excluded from our Eſteem. 'Tis yet a good Means to know People, by conſidering how they behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, both when their Fortune is at high Tide, and when 'tis at the loweſt Ebb. Which is to be ſeen in the next Article.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="part">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:96673:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> Of the Management of Proſperity and Adverſity.</head>
               <p>BY the Uſe a Gentleman makes of a ſwelling or a narrow Fortune, one may ſhrewdly gueſs at his Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and eaſily prompts what ſort of Opinion we are to have of him; if when his Sails are full he becomes fierce, and inſulting, or when the Storms of Adverſity blow hard, he is extremely ſunk in his Courage, and diſpirited; that Man, I'll warrant him, has a groveling Genius, and a mean Soul. But if he be unſhaken and ſteddy under the Torrent of his Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, or that the Flatteries of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune are not ſtrong eno' to abate his Goodneſs, to take off his Moderation, or to cramp his Civility, and his other Virtues, one may pronounce that Man has a Noble Reſolution, and a Soul
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:96673:73"/>that aſpires to its Original. Indeed without theſe two topping Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, a Man cannot ſhew in ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that we meet with, that Steadineſs, and Equality of Mind, which gives Evidence of the abſolute Empire we have over our Paſſions. To be able to follow, as Occaſion offers, the few Examples are to be found of ſuch an imperiſhable Virtue, let us ofren make this Reflection, that the Poſſeſſions of this Life are ſo inconſiderable, that they ought not to encourage our Pride, and the Afflictions we endure in it are ſo ſhort-liv'd, that we have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be dejected under 'em. Let us conſider alſo what an inexhauſtible Magazine of Happineſs, and a Fund of Glory that can never be worn out is deſign'd us, if we make that Uſe of Tranſitory Ills, and Comforts, which we ought; and now being convinc'd of theſe main Truths, let us look upon the various Turns of Fortune like Chriſtian Philoſophers, whether it be in its Declenſion, or its Zenith, let our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:96673:74"/>Humour be equally pois'd, and let us maintain a Conduct perpetually Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and proclaim to the whole World, that we are as capable ro ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain the Weight of Greatneſs, as we we are to bear evenly, and with Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, Court-Diſgraces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIII.</hi> Of Credential Letters, ſigning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers with Blanks.</head>
               <p>IN the Age we live in, a Man had need have his Wits well about him, not to be cully'd by Cheats, and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; for even thoſe in whom we repoſe an entire Confidence, are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the Van of our Deceivers; wherefore a Gentleman had need be very well aſſur'd of the Integrity of thoſe to whom he gives Letters of Credence; 'tis my Opinion alſo, that tho 'tis neceſſary to give ſuch ſort of Letters, yet they ought always to be accompanied with Inſtructions that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:96673:74"/>ſhall be clear, ſpecial, and which ſhall alſo deſcend to minute particulars, to the end, that they who are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated to manage an Affair, may not have any Evaſion to creep out at, if to ſerve their own private Ends they ſhall offer to make a falſe ſtep in the negotiating of their Buſineſs.</p>
               <p>As for Letters with Blanks, to be fill'd up at the Diſcretion of a Party, I would never truſt any Body with ſuch, and whoſoever ſhall reflect, that thereby he puts his Liberty, his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, his Life in the power of another, will ſurely have a great Care how he expoſeth whatſoever is dear to him in the World, upon a Bottom that is ſo liable to chouſe him, and which an ill Man may ſo eaſily employ to an ill Purpoſe, a Gentleman muſt alſo never give Certificates to any Man living, of the Service, and good Conduct of another; when he has no Proofs to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticate what he advances; ſuch Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monials are unjuſt, when they are given without knowing a warrantable ground
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:96673:75"/>for it, becauſe by this means Rewards come to be miſplac'd on thoſe who don't deſerve 'em. Beſides, if it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens afterward that ſuch People abuſe the Favours their Prince has conferr'd on 'em, they are troubled, but too late; for having been the unhappy Inſtruments to procure 'em that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, when they had ſo ſlender an Aſſurance of the Worth of the Perſons Recommended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIV.</hi> Of Curioſity.</head>
               <p>TO be curious is commendable, when nothing is deſign'd by it, but to be let into the Knowledge of of what is Profitable and Honeſt; but it is of a dangerous Conſequence when it tranſports us too far, and that it puts us upon Enquiries, which either contribute to our undoing, or at moſt can do us no good; let us be buſie in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:96673:75"/>every thing that tends to give the laſt Hand to our Condition; let us inform our ſelves throughly of every ſtep of our Duty; let us ſpur on our Underſtanding to the utmoſt to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern it well, and to have a great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in the Profeſſion we have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd; nothing is of greater Uſe than for every Man to be accompliſh'd in his Calling: 'Tis by this that Men now adays are diſtinguiſh'd from the Crowd, and tho they are wrap'd up in Gloomineſs, may ſpeedily hope for Shun-ſhine. He, that by a vain Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, or to have the Vogue of a Perſon of univerſal Acquirements, will dive into too many things, will never rightly digeſt any, and reaps no other Fruit of his Labour, and tedious Study, but a ſuperficial Knowledge of ſeveral things, which often are fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to his Circumſtances of Life. Will Men never be perſuaded to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſee in what's material? Here's a Religious Man who ought inceſſantly to fathom the Depths of the Holy
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:96673:76"/>Scriptures, thereby to enrich his Mind with Knowledge that ſpeaks its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Author, has infatuated himſelf with Judicial Aſtrology, has thrown away whole Nights and Days in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Aſtronomical Tables, and to look into the different Aſpects of the Planets, from thence to calculate Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivities; what Folly is it to preſume to unriddle what ſhall happen by the help of an Art that leans only on the trifling Imaginations of ſome whimſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dotards? The moſt famous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers acknowledge no other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple but Experience, and which is the greater Jeſt, 'tis that very Experience which condemns 'em; ſeeing that almoſt every Day expoſeth how monſtrous ſuch Predictions are. Another Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematician ſpends himſelf to find out the ſquaring of the Circle, or the Whirl of perpetual Motion, when he ſhould be buſied in perfecting thoſe parts of the Mathematicks, which help forward many Arts neceſſary to accommodate human Life. Up ſtarts a
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:96673:76"/>Chymiſt, who might ſerve the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, if he ſtuck only to what was uſeful in his Profeſſion; but he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, muſt be all agog for the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher's Stone, he dreams of nothing elſe but to get this great Work, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering himſelf that he ſhall quickly change every thing into Gold, like <hi>Midas</hi> in the Fable. What a ſtrange Infatuation poſſeſſes Men, that they will toil ſo hard, and with ſo much Paſſion to unlock thoſe Myſteries, which the Almighty would have dill lodg'd in their pre-ordain'd Secreſie? Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'tis a very criminal Curioſity, that can bewitch 'em to diſſolve their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in their Furnaces, to overpaſs their real Duties, and to conſume to no purpoſe a Life, that has ſo many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Minutes to be guarded, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd with the moſt Jealous Care.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="part">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:96673:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LV.</hi> To ſhun the Converſation of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines and Cowards.</head>
               <p>DIſcourſe, back'd with Example, is ſo very prevalent, that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to reſiſt the Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which it makes; wherefore 'tis of great uſe to avoid the Company of Looſe-Livers, and who publickly ſet up for Atheiſm; for beſides, that every ſuch Entercourſe would ruine our own Reputation; their lewd Speeches, their Sets of falſe Maxims, and the Contagion of their Examples, would at firſt Daſh deprave our beſt Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and inſenſibly corrupt our Souls, and after the Advances of a few Steps would precipitate us into the common Shore of Misfortunes, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch ſort of People ſink them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; 'tis moreover one of the Rules of Prudence, never to hold Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:96673:77"/>with Cowards, and the Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearted, who are generally over-run with Scruples, and Superſtition; as their Diſtemper is infectious, they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſhed down to their Aſſociateſ their own anxious Fears, and Thorny Doubts, which diffract the Mind, and ſtave it off from taking an adequate Dimenſion of Things. Theſe Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries, and Fits of Irreſolution, excite frivolous Suſpicions in us, which, as weak as they are, do yet diſcompoſe us, diveſt us of the Liberty of our Minds, and rob us of the Tranquillity of our Souls, without a Conjunction of which we can neither know how to make the belt Choice, nor to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace what we have choſen with an entire Confidence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="part">
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:96673:78"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LVI.</hi> Not to uſe Reſerves, but in Caſes of Neceſſity.</head>
               <p>WHen there is no firm Reaſon to give Birth to our Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it ought to ſtand for an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Law, that we ſhould act with Openneſs; to what purpoſe is it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to put on the Foxes Skin, to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect to ſpeak in the Clouds, to talk like the Oracles of <hi>Delphos,</hi> when there there is no occaſion to juſtifie ſuch a myſterious Cant; this only ſerves to ſpirit on others to ſuſpect you; whence it happens, that tho Subtilty might ſometimes be neceſſary, yet it will do him no Service, who wears it out with continual Practice, becauſe every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is ready arm'd againſt his Craft; the Deſigns of a Man who is currently ſtamp'd for ſlineſs, are the moſt eaſie to untwiſt; for as every Body ſuſpects
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:96673:78"/>him, and watches him narrowly, it ſeldom falls out, but that all his Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are broken. I do not intend here thoſe Wiles which are only us'd with Deſign to ſurprize, and cheat, every one throws ſomething into the Scale to condemn 'em; I would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of that tricking, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly in it ſelf is no ill; and I ſay, as innocent, as it is; 'tis but ſeldom to be employ'd, and that too by the Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of Neceſſity; The general Rule to be given in this Caſe is this, that Tricks are never to be us'd to impoſe upon any Body, but only to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine thoſe who make a fraudulent Attack.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LVII.</hi> Of the Death of a Friend.</head>
               <p>NO Grief ſtabs in ſo ſenſible a part, as that which a Gentleman feels when he loſeth a deſerving Perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:96673:79"/>whom, and himſelf, Love was wrought up to the higheſt Pitch of Sincerity; Such a Loſs wounds the deeper, foraſmuch as 'tis irreparable; and a Man had need of the Conſtancy, or rather the Inſenſibility of a Stoick, if he be not touch'd to the quick with it. Altho ſuch a Sorrow might ſeem defenſible, yet 'tis good to call in the Succors of Faith, and the Beams of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to dart Comfort into our Shades, and to ſweeten the Bitterneſs which we then moſt exquiſitely taſte, and to take this along with us, that in ſuch a doleful Scene, ſhedding of Tears is not eno' to diſcharge the Truſt of a true friendſhip; there ought to be beſides, ſome ſacred Repoſitory dearly to lodge the Remembrance of his Friend; and as the beſt Badge, that his Memory is honor'd, to ſee the faithful Execution of his laſt Will, to aſſiſt his Family, if 'tis diſtreſs'd, and above all, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the Almighty, that his Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the next Life may even be double to his Hopes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="part">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:96673:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LVIII.</hi> At the Court, Diffidence is neceſſary.</head>
               <p>HE that ſteps into a Court, ought to look upon himſelf in an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Country, where a thouſand Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcades are laid to enſnare him; 'tis there where Gentlemen are moſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and leaſt Sincere; let us ſuſpect their artificial Careſſes, and that they wheedle us to confide more in 'em than we have reaſon to do; and let us remember, that 'tis their common Courſe to give us the Picture of their Minds quite different from the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, ſuch a one ſmiles on you, and makes all the Overtures of your hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servant, when at the ſame time he waits only for the Opportunity ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to undo you. Not to be cully'd by theſe treacherous Friends, a dextrous Courtier equally conceals his Deſigns, and his Thoughts, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:96673:80"/>in what relates to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Great Men, he cloaks his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that his Rivals may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, the Execution of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and ſmothers his Sentiments, leſt hiſ Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhould make a wrong Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of 'em, and give him Trouble amongſt thoſe who are in a Poſt to do him a Miſchief. You will ſay, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, that 'tis irkſome to be always upon your Guard, and to be ſhy of Perſons whom you are oblig'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with every day; I agree it, but at Court ſuch Precautions ate not to be avoided, And after all, 'tis prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to be circumſpect, and reſerv'd both in Words and Actions, tho 'tis at the Expence of a little Uneaſineſs, than to lay himſelf liable to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd by unboſoming himſelf to thoſe whoſe Fidelity has not paſſed the Teſt. Nevertheleſs, I do not encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage ſuch a general ſuſpicion, as ſhall admit of no Exception; I own that a diſcreet Friend, of an approv'd Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is to be rely'd on; but till a Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:96673:80"/>can be ſo happy to find one ſuch, the ſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t way not to be chous'd, is to truſt no Body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIX.</hi> Of Paſſions in thoſe who are well in Years.</head>
               <p>EVery Gentleman is ſo much the more taking, as his Way corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds with his Age, and the Rank which he holds in the World; ſo we are pleaſed with a Big and Majeſtick Air in a Monarch, with Gravity upon the Bench, with a lofty and fierce Meen in the General of an Army: Thus we love to ſee Sprightlineſs in a Child, Activity in a young Man, but expect an old Man to be ſerious: But contrary wiſe, a Perſon is ſo much the more nauſeous, as he departs from his proper Character; wherefore we ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor to ſee youthful Paſſions tempered with aged Snow, but Love, eſpecially
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:96673:81"/>at that time aday makes a Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; indeed what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And who can forbear Laughing, when they ſee a Man act a part that is all ſtrain'd 'Tis a great Unhappineſs for a Man to cancel in a few Minutes all thoſe Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions of Glory and Honor, which he had beeen tugging for all his Life long; yet this is the Practice of old Pops, who would, ſpark it as they did when they were blooming, and who are no wiſer, nor have any more Command of themſeves at Sixty, than they had at Eighteen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LX.</hi> Of Counſel.</head>
               <p>IT ſtands them much in ſtead, who move in a high Orb, to ſtoop to the Advices that are giv'n 'em, and to ſuſpend their Determination till Truth
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:96673:81"/>can be ſifted out; for as this Method often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs things in a Right Light; 'tis the Prudence of a Prime Miniſter, of a General of an Army, of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of a Place, to entertain Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to reward 'em liberally, if they make good what they propoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but if to create a good Opinion of their Wit, and Skill to unriddle an Intrigue, they give falſe Accounts of Things, and ſhall even dare, out of Hatred or Envy, to faſten Crimes on Men of Honor, and Worth, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be laſh'd ſeverely as Make-Bates, whoſe Jugglings may be of dangerous Conſequence, both for the State, and for thoſe who are over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach'd by 'em.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXI.</hi> The Duties of Perſons advanc'd to a High Poſt.</head>
               <p>THey who ſtand on the upper Ground, are begirt with ſo many Cares, are fatigu'd with ſo much
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:96673:82"/>Labour, and are oblig'd to ſummon ſo much Vigilance, and Application to their Aid, that they are rather illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Slaves, who are mounted to be wrack'd by State-Hurricanes, than ſuch as can enjoy the undiſturb'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their Deſires; but Great Men ſtruggle hard againſt any Rhetorick that would perſuade 'em of the Force of this Truth; he that ſhould tell 'em, that the more they are rais'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Level, the more in ſome ſenſe they have impair'd their Freedom; the more Buſineſs they have upon their Hands, the move wary Steps to tread, and the more ſtrict Meaſures to adhere to, would beſpeak 'em in a barbarous Language, whence they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver dream'd of being attack'd; they look only on the Gawdy Part, the Honors they receive by great Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Power they afford to Cruſh, without ever turning the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective, and attending to the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and Toils which are inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably annex'd to 'em; There are very
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:96673:82"/>few would have the Hardineſs to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture on thoſe Bulky Charges, if they conſider'd how difficult it is to keep their Character untainted in the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of 'em; 'tis not eno' for him that is got into the Saddle, to have the fineſt Embelliſhments of Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if the nobleſt Inclinations of the Mind do not bear 'em compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſteer 'em to the moſt credita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Advantage. Moreover, he can ſcarce be without any one Virtue, particularly Piety, Prudence, and Moderation, are as neceſſary as his Cloths, he is bound to keep the Reins ſtraight upon his Manners, not to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any Slips in his Behaviour, to countenance his baffled Virtue, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly to promote his Countries Good, to ſet forward the Intereſts of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to contribute all he can to the Removal of publick and private Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, to puniſh Vice with Severity, and to give ample Compenſation to the Deſerving; to let Equity run thro' all his Actions, to be intent, watchful,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:96673:83"/>and unwearied. In a word, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice his own Quiet, for his King's Service, and his Countrey's Peace. They who are to adminiſter a Prince's Juſtice to his People, to command his Armies, or to be his Lord Lieutenants, are indiſpenſably oblig'd to do all theſe; for without it 'tis not poſſible for 'em to avoid Diſgraces, to adorn their Station, or to poſſeſs the People, that they have deſerv'd ſolid Glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXII.</hi> Not to give haſty Anſwers in weighty Matters.</head>
               <p>'TIS a Raſhneſs of dangerous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to reply upon the Spot in Matters of Moment, without a wide Capacity, aſſiſted by a long Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; and tho a Man were Maſter of theſe two great Advantages, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, if Opportunity can allow it, 'twere better to take time to meditate
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:96673:83"/>what Anſwer is fit to be return'd to the Propoſal. Let no Man, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge a guilty Pride, ſtrut that he does then give Evidence of the Greatneſs, and Facility of his Mind, in diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too haſtily, that which deſerves to be examin'd at leiſure, in ſuch Caſes great Miſcarriages ariſe, eſpecially when the Intereſt of the Publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on 'em.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIII.</hi> Not to Protect the Wicked.</head>
               <p>NOthing looks ſo fine, as to do good to all the World, not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting our greateſt Enemies; 'tis the wicked alone that a Man muſt never defend; this would be, to declare himſelf a Supporter of Vice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to renounce the Quality of a Man of Honor; a Miniſter, who furniſheth the Impious with Credit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Authority, by preferring 'em to
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:96673:84"/>Offices, makes himſelf reſponſible for all the Excurſions they may be guilty of in the Abuſe of their Power; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that God will ſcourge ſuch an unjuſt and faithleſs Miniſter, the Prince has reaſon to frown on that Traitor, that ſcatters his Authority amongſt Subjects that are ſo unworthy, that in all Appearance they are the likelieſt Inſtruments to unhinge the Realm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIV.</hi> How a Man is to carry himſelf to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Ungrateful.</head>
               <p>NEver let our Reſentment of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful Returns, tranſport us to tax 'em for that lewd Indulgence, Reproaches and Contumelies are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper Engines to work 'em into an Acknowledgment of their Fault: On the contrary, if they find us running 'em down in company, the Indifference
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:96673:84"/>which they had for us, is preſently metamorphos'd into Hatred, and they immediately declare War againſt us: the only way to make 'em look at home, is to treat 'em with the ſame Civility as uſual, without ſhewing that you are touch'd by the Affront of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. This mild Procedure does Wonders, this quickly melts 'em into Repentance; for having diſregarded thoſe perſons who have ſo repeatedly oblig'd 'em, and at laſt has wrought a thoro Reformation in their Conduct. Is it not better to win over People by a Generoſity which affects 'em ſo much the more, as they are ſenſible that they don't deſerve it, than to irritate 'em by our Checks and Neglects of 'em, or by a diſdainful Pride to compell 'em to be our Enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="part">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:96673:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXV.</hi> What muſt be obſerved in great Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings.</head>
               <p>IN Great Deſigns we often throw at all, either for Loſs, or Gain; as therefore the Conſequences are very dangerous, if the Caſt does not prove ſucceſsful; great Precaution is to be us'd before we put it in the Power of a Die to decide our Fate. 'Tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that a Man never ought to form any important Deſign, without he concludes himſelf capable to carry it on dextrouſly, and bring it to a happy Period. Wherefore a quick Genius will not do the Work, Conſtancy and Diligence in the executive Part are alſo neceſſary; moreover, 'tis requiſite, that thoſe we make choice of to be aſſiſted in great Enterprises have a Stock of Judgment, and Courage; for if they know not to apply the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:96673:85"/>Wheels of Buſineſs to one another, the leaſt Obſtacle ſtops 'em, any Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in their way perplex 'em, and blunt their Purſuit, and if they flag in their Reſolution, the ſight of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger aſtoniſhes 'em, they turn tail; and a Man has the Diſſatisfaction, that he is ſhipwrack'd by their Cowardiſe. Thoſe who accompany us in ſuch Matters, ought to be Men of Honor; for I know there is nothing to fear from perſons of that Character, and that there needs no other Engagement to 'em when they have given their Parole. Nevertheleſs, when any Matter of mighty Moment is to be tranſacted, by reaſon of the Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Men, in the choice of whom we are ſo eaſily impos'd upon, and the interfering of ſo many croſs Accidents, I think 'tis neceſſary for common ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſet down in writing the Terms of our Agreement, and the ſeveral Reſolutions concerted, and alſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs 'em in ſuch plain Terms, that there may be no Room left for Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:96673:86"/>If things miſcarry, and (it happens) that a Man be betray'd or deſerted, the producing of ſuch Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings will clear his Reputation, they will teſtifie, that ſuch a one was not a Party in the Faults of others, and that the Unſucceſsfulneſs of Affairs is only imputable to themſelves, either for want of Preſence of Mind in Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or becauſe delivering themſelves over to their own Whimſies, they have ſtagger'd in the executing what they had reſolv'd; Secreſie is of no leſs Weight in great Deſigns, than what I have been ſpeaking of, which I ſhall make appear in the following Maxim.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVI.</hi> Of a Secret.</head>
               <p>THE Greateſt Politicians would ſit brooding on their Intrigues to no purpoſe, if the Avenues to their Counſel were not well guarded. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:96673:86"/>Deſigns the beſt laid do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly come to Maturity, when thoſe are capable to unrip 'em, whoſe Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt 'tis to oppoſe 'em: let a Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cert his Meaſures never ſo juſtly, ſuch will be ſure to break thro' 'em all, and obviate every Artifice that is contriv'd againſt 'em. 'Tis chiefly at Court that a Man ought to be in ſome ſort impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrable; Wits are there ſo ſubtle, that they will decypher by a Motion, by a Word, by a Look, what you wou'd have remain in Pot-hook Hand; how many Projects do we ſee abortive, merely becauſe they who ought to diſſemble their Intentions, moſt art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſuffer themſelves to be founded before-hand by the Sharpers? others there are, who for want of Judgment or Experience lay themſelves open at firſt Daſh, without conſidering to what Hazards ſuch an Ingenuity does expoſe 'em. To be plain, there is ſuch a ſorry Remnant of Plain Dealing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men, that a Man cannot be too much upon his Guard; and one
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:96673:87"/>had need try 'em exactly before he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locks the Cabinet of his Breaſt to 'em. Yet all agree, that every one is bound to retain the Secret he is made a Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of, and that it is a ſacred <hi>Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> by no means to be rudely blab'd; but where's the Man who does not encroach on this Law, or rather that does not make Inroads upon it, if he can be a Gainer by ſuch a barbarous Infidelity? When I ſay, that a Secret is an inviolable and ſacred Thing, I do not pretend nevertheleſs, that this Propoſition is univerſally true, and is a Rule to be laid down without Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; for Example, if after having enjoyn'd me Secreſie, one has imparted to me ſome criminal Matter which he is taking in Hand, I ought, 'tis true, to do all I am able to divert him from it; but if I cannot ſucceed, and that I have no other way to defeat him of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing ſuch a pernicious Reſolution, then I become licens'd to reveal the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret: The Reaſon of it lies here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when I aſſur'd him that I would
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:96673:87"/>communicate to no Body what he committed to my keeping, I believ'd him uncapable of doing any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming an Honeſt Man, ſo that I did not tie my ſelf up to be ſilent, but upon ſuppoſition that he would not defile my Underſtanding, by making me the Truſtee of a ſcandalous Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Beſides, every Promiſe, made contrary to a precedent Obligation, is void in it ſelf; now if I have engag'd to ſtifle ſome monſtrous Birth, ſuch an Engagement runs counter to one of my firſt Obligations, ſeeing 'tis contrary to that Law of Nature ſo profitable, and ſo well grounded, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all Men with might and main to oppoſe the Progreſs of Evil, and to nip budding Vice, this Promiſe then is null, and I am diſpens'd from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it. One may ſee by this, and by the Examples which occur in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, that 'tis dangerous to be the Confident of anothers Secrets, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of thoſe of Great Men, where 'tis ten to one if it be not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:96673:88"/>with State-Intereſts; wherefore every wiſe Man ought to get cleare o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this Truſt as much as he is able, not that we muſt reject that Confidence which a true Friend ſhews he has in us, by turning the Inſide of his Heart outward; for, as I take it for granted, that this Friend of mine is both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, and virtuous, ſo I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that he will never impart any thing ſo heinous to me, that by a Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of Obligation I am to reveal; then the Law of a Secret ſtands in full force; and a Man muſt ſooner ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice every thing that is dear to him, than once violate ſo religious a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVII.</hi> Of Hope, and Deſpair.</head>
               <p>MEN who ſhould only put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Conduct of refin'd Reaſon, commonly paſs ſuch a
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:96673:88"/>Judgment on things, as moſt corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds with their Humour and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; ſo the preſumptuous, who are us'd to flatter themſelves, grow ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſuaded, that they ſhall obtain every thing they deſire; and the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, who diſtruſt their own ſhadow, and with ſuſpicion combat the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Attacks of others, almoſt ever deſpair of having their Deſigns crown'd with Succeſs. Let us diligently avoid theſe dangerous Extremes, for Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and an extravagant Reliance, do equally prompt Men to neglect the Means that may bring their Affairs to a happy Iſſue. Does not Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence every day inform us, that by this ſteerage it happens, that often a Man's Imagination is balk'd by a quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Event? whence it follows, that many perſons gull'd by vain Hopes, or depreſs'd by unreaſonable Fears, are either ſuddenly on the High Ropes, or vex'd to the Guts by an impertinent Anticipation: Theſe Reaſons, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, ſhould perſuade us, that when
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:96673:89"/>we have laid out all our ſtock of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in order to accompliſh our Aims, we are oblig'd to remain as much as is poſſible in a profound Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, without ever being under the Hatches of a ſlaviſh Fear, an empty Hope, or a tormenting Deſpair: But ſo, that tho we neglect nothing that may bring about our Ends, yet at the ſame time we may buckle on our neceſſary Armour, to prevent any untoward Afterclaps, upon ſuppoſition, that they are not attended with Succeſs. If we wou'd be thus fore-arm'd, any Advantage we ſhould gain would have double Charms, in as much as we leaſt of all expected it, and the Miſchief would both be leſs, and we ſhould not be half ſo ſenſible of it, becauſe we had been before-hand in our Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to encounter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="part">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:96673:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXVIII.</hi> To take Virtue's Part.</head>
               <p>OPpreſs'd Virtue is an Object which ſenſibly touches a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Man, and makes him employ all his own Credit to buoy up the Intereſts of the Impotent, which are puſh'd at with ſo much Injuſtice, in order to be run down: But that Generoſity is thin ſown in this Age. With what Unconcernedneſs do Men ſee Vice tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant; and are tame Spectators, when by an artificial Management it erects its lofty Head upon the Ruines of humble Virtue? And even ſuch as might eaſily interpoſe to hinder the innocent Sacrifice, durſt not pull back the Hand of the unjuſt Ruffian that is the Executioner. Nevertheleſs, let what will happen, methinks we are oblig'd privately to advertize thoſe who have the Sword of Authority, of the Frauds that are made uſe of to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:96673:90"/>Innocence, or at leaſt our ſelves to ſet up for its Champions, if we have but any thing tutelar about us to produce; doubtleſs an Action ſo met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſome will ſet Obloquy on our Backs, but it ſignifies nothing; for Men of Honor in this Inſtance will he on our ſide; But after all, put caſe that there were a great deal to be riſqu'd by the Attempt, can we ſuffer for a better Cauſe than to put Virtue in the Throne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXIX.</hi> Of Irreſolution.</head>
               <p>THoſe who level at no ſix'd Mark, and are always fluctuating in what they are to go about, ſtrole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in the World, as Travellers who ſtraggle in a Wood, where they know not which way to turn; we muſt ſtrive betimes to know well the different Conditions of Civil Society, and then embrace that which we ſhall judge
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:96673:90"/>ſuits us beſt; ſometimes we have ſeen People that have worn out their Lives, before they have ever thought of deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining 'em to an-Employment: Yet the Thread of Life is ſo ſhort, and the Time we have to ſpin it, ſo value<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that 'tis perfect Theft to ſteal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way any part of it, to hover in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of chuſing a Profeſſion. There is another ſort of Unſteadineſs, or rather Irreſolution, which is not altogether ſo prejudicial, but which does a great deal of Harm; it conſiſts in not knowing what to reſolve upon Buſineſs, and to anſwer Emergencies as they ariſe; to be then in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence when we are hurried; and that we are preſs'd to give a quick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of our Thoughts. I allow it to be very uſeful to examine things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we undertake 'em; but when you may endanger the Succeſs of your Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, by Licenſing an Opportunity to ſlide by, (and many hopeful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have prov'd addle, for want of timely Diligence to ripen 'em) 'tis an unpardonable Omiſſion to be drawling
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:96673:91"/>out Time in tedious Debates, what you are to do, to ſhew you have Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney like a Drone, but can't recover your Sting; Cowards and Half-witted People have this Fault, ſo that of all Men living, you are to chuſe 'em laſt for the Execution of great Affairs, which are often loſt by delay, and which require a Man that has Nerves for Application, as well as Bones for Fatigue, that has an exalted Courage founded upon a peremptory, and clear Judgment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXX.</hi> Not to be Raſh in Judging.</head>
               <p>HOW come Men to ſuck in ſuch Variety of Errors, what's the Reaſon ſo many deliver up themſelves to the Conduct of Falſe Principles; 'tis becauſe they will not be at the Expence of diving for Truth in things purely ſpeculative, nor weigh which ſide is moſt eligible in practical Matters?
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:96673:91"/>Juſtice and Truth are not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood at the firſt Glance; the Clouds which Paſſions throw over our Minds, and a Load of Prejudices block up our way to a diſtinct Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of what is both true and juſt: So that often 'tis only an exact and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Enquiry that can uſher us into the ſatisfaction of ſetting up for Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverers. Men of the greateſt Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are ſometimes put upon, in ſpight of all their Reflections; what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come then of thoſe Wits below Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard, who ſound nothing to the Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, and do only ramble (as I may ſo ſay) over the Surface of things? 'Tis of the utmoſt of Importance to us to ſhun Precipitation in our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for from hence Hereſies and Plots have their Riſe, it ſprings Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, and breeds Factions, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex Mens Underſtandings, and break in upon their Repoſe; 'tis this over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haſtineſs, join'd with the latent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of our Minds, which ſways us to put a miſchievous Interpretation on the Actions of others, tho it be to
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:96673:92"/>overthrow a Maxim grounded upon the Law of Nature, which commands us to take every thing by the beſt Handle we can find. Beſides, Self-conceitedneſs, and Croſsneſs, Vices equally dangerous in Morality, and Civil Matters, are the ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitants of that Raſhneſs I have been ſpeaking of, wherefore let us carefully avoid it. And ſince bounteous Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven has vouchſaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Reaſon for our Guide, let us judge of nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out its aſſiſtance, and never let us be carried down ſtream by the impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Torrent of our Paſſions, which engaging us Hand over Head to make a Choice, reduce us to that wretched Neceſſity, either to forfeit our Word, or our Duty. A Firſt-Rate Wit falls into this Errour, if he preſſeth on too forwardly; whereas one of the middle Form, who ſurveys things nearly, and with leiſure, perceives that which had eſcap'd the Obſervation of the moſt clear-ſighted, but who were leſs heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to detect it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="part">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:96673:92"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXI.</hi> How we ought to treat them who have any way been aſſiſtant to us.</head>
               <p>WHen two, or more, have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certed an Undertaking, and that all have contributed to its Succeſs, he who ſhall monopolize the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and Glory pf it, has very little Honor, and Equity in him; and well, is it not juſt, that they who have born a part in the Fatigue, and have waded thro' the thickeſt of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhould be ſharers alſo in what's to be got by an Undertaking. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in theſe Caſes dares falſly brag, that all the Glory of a happy Succeſs is owing to him, loſeth by his Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty much more than he will get; for beſides that by praiſing himſelf, he purchaſeth much more Contempt, than Eſteem; the Complaints which they vent of his Pride, and Breach of Faith, who have ſerv'd him ſo faithfully, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:96673:93"/>whoſe Services in the mean time he takes ſuch Pains to undervalue, to make his own look with a better Grace, do ſo blaſt his Credit in the World, that no Body will venture to back him in his Deſigns. But on the other ſide, all ſatisfactorily vie with each other, to promote and advance the Deſigns of ſuch, who, without e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver trumpeting what they have done themſelves, charge all the Succeſs of their Enterprises oh the account of the Worth or good Conduct of their Partners, and ſuch an extreme Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is ſo far from diminiſhing the Luſtre of their commendable Actions, that it enhaunces to the beſt Advantage the Deſert of 'em.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXII.</hi> Of Unforeſeen Accidents.</head>
               <p>SOmetimes it happens, that an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which we were not aware of, breaks the Neck of the ſtricteſt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:96673:93"/>Meaſures we can take, rand throws an Obſtacle almoſt inſuperable, to baffle the Execution of Deſigns laid with the beſt Skill, 'tis not poſſible to preſcribe the preciſe Rules of what is to be done on theſe Occaſions; this depends on the Poſture Mens Minds, and the Things to be adjuſted are in at that Time: I ſhall only ſay, that as long time of Deliberation is to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as the Affairs themſelves can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford; and after that, we muſt boldly go on with what carries the faireſt Marks of Advantage, and execute it with as much Aſſurance, as if every point had been under ſcrutiny more maturely. 'Tis in ſuch difficult Jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures that an exemplary Courage is in ſeaſon, 'tis then that we may make a clear judgment what ſort of Genius he has, who ſteers the Undertaking; Happy is that Man that has ſo much Ability to pitch upon good Expedients, and if preſerving a ſtanch temper in the midſt of Danger, and the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moil of Affairs, he diſtributes every where his Orders with that admirable
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:96673:94"/>Preſence of Mind, which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up ſo much in the blazoning of Great Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXIII.</hi> Of Favours, of Recompences, and of the Diſpoſal of Offices.</head>
               <p>WHen thoſe who preſide, turn the Stream of their Kindneſs, and canton their Employments only where Favour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ays 'em; 'tis a growing Miſchief <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o that Realm where they have the Adminiſtration: This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartens Gentlemen of Merit, who ſee plainly, that what is thus ſcatter'd amongſt others, is in ſome ſort ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd from 'em; and as the principal Employments are exrcis'd by thoſe who have no reaſonable Title to' em, particular Men ſuffer by the Bargain; and the main Body of the Kingdom receives a very notable Blow by it: But when by the Methods of true Policy Rewards are only granted to 'em, who claim 'em by their unwearied
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:96673:94"/>Services, and that you cannot point at an Employment diſpos'd of, or a Poſt fill'd up, but at the ſame time you muſt tacitly own the Juſtice of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, every one is ſtimulated to mend his Worth being per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aded that his Fortune wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as his Virtue is triumphant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſides, it makes the publick Wheels turn more glibly; Peace and Joy reign throughout, and Order is maintained in all things; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe with whom the Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce has lodg'd his Authority, being honeſt Men, acquit themſelves of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with Exactneſs, and apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to make the People hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. We ſee now in <hi>France</hi> the Effect of this diſcreet Policy; the King gives every thing where Merit calls for't, but nothing on the ſcore of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. And this is the way that makes him ſo well ſerv'd, to the Envy of the World; and one may ſay, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Care which he has always took to make a wiſe Choice of his Miniſters, of the Generals of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and his other Officers, has not a
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:96673:95"/>little contributed to the Happineſs of his Subjects, and to advance himſelf to that high P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch of Glory and Power, where we now with Aſtoniſhment ſee him elevated.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXIV.</hi> Of the Way to Grant, or Refuſe Kindneſſes.</head>
               <p>THere are ſome who beſtow what is requir'd of 'em, but 'tis always either too late, or upon certain Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or with ſo ill a Grace, that the Receivers con 'em but very little Thanks for the Gift; if you have a Deſign to be a Benefactor, and that you would at the ſame time chain the Affection of the oblig'd to you, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs him with a Belief, that' tis in good earneſt you deſign to be his Friend; the diſcompos'd Air, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traint with which ſome Gentlemen communicate their Favours, leſſens more than half the Price of the Benefit
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:96673:95"/>received; whereas he who has the Art of gaining Votaries, the very manner of making it, is more agreeable than the Preſent it ſelf; and is more deeply impreſſive on a Mind that is ſenſible of any either thing beſides Intereſt. 'Tis of no leſs Advantage to know decently how to refuſe a Peti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ner; that is to ſay, to ſw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> by the Softneſs of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and by civil and obliging Methods, whatſoever is diſguſtful, and grating in a Refuſal; a civil Gentleman is ſo griev'd that he can't content every Supplicant, he deals ſo well with perſons that make applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to him, that he plants a Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of himſelf even in thoſe, whom he ſends away not gratified in their Demands, and they go off perſuaded, that 'tis none of his Fault that they have not an entire ſatisfaction in what they came for; ſo that they ſhew themſelves not leſs oblig'd for being deny'd with Regret, than for being treated with Satisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="part">
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:96673:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXV.</hi> Of a Retir'd, and a Court-Life.</head>
               <p>HOW ſweet is the Life of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe, how calm and inviting is it? a Man who lives in Retirement, eſtrang'd from Objects which might kindle his Paſſions, enjoys a profound Tranquillity; which both gives him an opportunity to purſue Truth, and at the ſame time an eaſie Conqueſt of it; 'tis in Solitude that a Man is us'd to make a ſound Judgment of every thing that paſſes under the File; his Mind there takes a freer Range, and his Underſtanding is at full ſtretch, he takes in a thouſand Things by Reading, and Meditation, and is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver weary with contemplating the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perfections, which ſhine ſo won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully both in the Order of Nature, and in the ſuperinduc'd Bounty of his Grace. On the contrary, it ſeems <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat he who poſſeſſes a conſiderable
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:96673:96"/>Charge has Reaſon to lament: How many Cares, ſay they, how many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigues, what Agitations of Mind haunt the Men in great Offices? I grant it, yet I believe that the greateſt Favourite of Fortune, who has the neceſſary Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications worthily to diſcharge the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Employment, taſtes even in that Condition Pleaſures, which much ballance the Degree of his Sufferings. For if he executes faithfully that Power he is inveſted with (as I ſuppoſe him to do) what Pleaſure does not he reap by ſerving his King, and Countrey to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, by defending the weak, by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Innocent under his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by aſſiſting the Poor, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Gentlemen of Merit. In a word, by employing his Wealth and Credit, to do good to an infinite number of diſtreſſed Gentlemen, who want the comfortable Influences of 'em. They who have Souls noble and generous eno' to make ſo good an Uſe of the Advantages of a full Fortune, and who beſides this have a vaſt Reach,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:96673:97"/>and a long Head, wherewith to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrate into Intrigues, are without doubt call'd to the Management of great Undertakings, and they ought to improve the rare Endowments in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Heaven has giv'n 'em for their Country's Good: Inferiour Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and a private Life are no ways ſuited to theſe Great Men, that can preſently diſcuſs a great Maſs of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; and therefore ſeem to be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on purpoſe to Govern others, but for thoſe who have only a common ſort of Virtue, and an Underſtanding of a mean Scantling, they may live in the Shades, and the Publick will be no Loſer by it; and if they are not ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd out of the Crowd, they ought not to ſtep up to a Condition diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion'd to the Strength, and Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of their Heads.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="part">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:96673:97"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVI.</hi> What Sentiments the Uſe of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhould inſpire us with.</head>
               <p>'TIS odd to imagine, that thoſe Creatures which contribute ſo much to our Ruine, might not, if we had the skill to manage 'em aright, do more for our Preſervation? and if we confin'd our ſelves to a juſt Uſe of 'em, whatſoever we found valuable and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting in 'em would naturally engage our Affection to that Treaſury whence all are inrich'd; but where an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or a worſe Scene open'd, this would abate our Eſteem, and wean us from a cloſe purſuit of 'em. The Beauty of the Univerſe, and particularly the Charms of reaſonable Creatures would adminiſter to us ſome Idea of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Beauty of God, and would forcibly carry us to deſire a perpetual Union with him. Wit, Power, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Diſcretion, Equity, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:96673:98"/>other celebrated Qualities of Men, would irreſiſtably ſway us to admire the Divine Perfections, which are the Source of all our Virtues, and the Principle from whence every Good we poſſeſs, is deriv'd. The mix'd Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which we taſte on Earth, and which we wooe with ſo much Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, tho they have a great deal of Bitterneſs in 'em, put us upon think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how double refin'd thoſe are which glorifi'd Saints enjoy; and might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to labour to be added to that Celeſtial Quire. On the other ſide the Diſorders which peſter the World, might exſtinguiſh our Deſire of adhering to 'em; the Miſeries of this Life, and its ſhort Duration, might make us fully ſenſible, that Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in good earneſt is not in it. To conclude, the Frailties, and Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of thoſe amongſt whom we live, might ſtave us oft from loving any Body upon any other Conſideration, than merely for the ſake of pure Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and thus the moſt unbridl'd Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions would never run away with our
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:96673:98"/>Quiet, the dazling Splendour of this ſenſible Frame of Things would make little Impreſſion on our Minds; and the ſame Objects which moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly undermine our Happineſs, might be the proper Inſtruments to eſtabliſh it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVII.</hi> Of Baniſhment.</head>
               <p>EXile, to ſpeak properly, is no more than Change of Air, which ought to create no Diſturbance to a Man of an irreproachable Conduct, all Countries are equally good to Honeſt Men; where-ever they go, they find what is neceſſary to keep 'em a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, and this the Command of their Paſſions allows to be ſufficient; when therefore by ſome Reverſe of Fortune a Man is oblig'd to withdraw into a ſort of Wilderneſs, after having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways liv'd amidſt Court-Ceremony and Noiſe, he ought not to be in the murmuring Key, and bemoan a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dileſs
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:96673:99"/>Fate; this only alarms the Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by with the Complainer's Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. A Man ought rather to go off that Stage Gentilely, which he is no longer able to tread without ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling againſt a High Tide. Great Men indeed, are ſo diſingag'd in their Affections, that they can quit princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Employments with more eaſe than accept 'em; they know that they are ſo circumſtantiated, that 'tis difficult to perform the Truſt of 'em well, and as they did enjoy 'em with Indifference, they leave 'em ſedately, and with Chearfulneſs. The Accidents which deſpoi'ld 'em of 'em, and which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly paſs under the Name of Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and Diſgraces, they regard as the firſt Inlet of their Happineſs; for when they look back on the Entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a thouſand diſtracting Cares that had detain'd 'em, and ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſet free from the Agitations that are inſeparable from great Places, they begin to reliſh the Bleſſings of Liberty, and to enjoy the happy Calm of a Life refreſh'd with Peace and Innocence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="part">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:96673:99"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXVIII.</hi> Of Impriſonment.</head>
               <p>THE Caſe is much the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Impriſonment, and Exile; for thoſe Priſons where Men are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd with Neceſſaries for the Body, and where alſo a ſuitable Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Mind is provided, can be reckon'd only as Solitudes, where a Man may have no Interruption of his Quiet, if he will but temporize, but where he will be miſerable, if he will let Vexation or Sadneſs put him in a Ferment. When a Man has a clear Conſcience, 'tis a Miſtake for him to perſuade himſelf that he is unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, becauſe he can't take ſo free a Range as he could when he was at large: A <hi>Carthuſian</hi> is well ſatisfi'd in his Cell, tho he is prohibited to make any Excurſion; How comes that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout? Becauſe he has adopted that for a ſweet Courſe of Life, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:96673:100"/>look upon as a Slavery not to be endur'd; but he who is in Priſon has Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire eno' over himſelf to do the ſame thing, he ſhall not be more reſtrain'd, nor leſs free than the Religious Man; this would be to act like a reaſonable Agent; but the beſt Choice would be to do the Office of a Chriſtian, and to have no other Opinion of the Lives of Perſons of Quality, but what ſhould be reconcileable with our Religion. If I were not afraid, that I ſhould be apprehended for invading the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Office, I would introduce a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Paſſage of <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s, who, ſpeaking to the Chriſtians ſhut up in terrible Dungeons, for the ſake of their Faith, has theſe Words: <hi>Do not afflict your ſelves,</hi> ſays he, <hi>becauſe you are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the World; for if you were convinc'd, as you ought to be, that the World is a real Priſon, you would be much more free in your Priſons, than you would be in the World.</hi> Yet there are Priſoners, who innocently afflict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Confinement, becauſe they look upon the Condition wherein
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:96673:100"/>they are, not more a Puniſhment, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on 'em, than as the Triumph of their Perſecutors; but if any Grief ſprings from hence, 'tis only the Effect of their diſturb'd Imagination; 'tis to be conſider'd, whether Impriſonment in it ſelf is any great Ill, and if it does not lie in our Power to make a good Uſe of it, without ever diſquieting our Brains for what others think of it, whoſe Opinion can add nothing to our unhappy Load. 'Tis thus, that a Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Man puts things in the Scales, he always takes 'em on the Right Side, and by ſo doing, he becomes happy to his Wiſhes, in that ſtate, where the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerning Crowd by a corrupt Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar compute him miſerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="part">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:96673:101"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXIX.</hi> Of the Love, and Imitation of Jeſus Christ.</head>
               <p>JEſus Chriſt knowing the Corruption of Men, and that his Word was not ſharp eno' to Lance the Tumour of their Pride, nor ſufficiently impreſſive to purge their Minds ſo full of Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, was not contented to indulge them a Law, all Divine like himſelf, to keep their Manners in a due Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; but fell upon the Practice like a bright Example, beckoning them to follow that Holy Life: To the Power of that Exemplar he hath given us, he has ſuperadded the Aſſiſtance of his Grace, without which we could never get our Weather-beaten Veſſels into that Port of Happineſs he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd us; and that which ought par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to touch us to the quick, is, that a pure and diſintereſted Charity was the Foundation of all that he did
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:96673:101"/>for us, that God who found in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the never flowing Fountain of his own Felicity, needed none of the impotent Company of his Revolted Creatures; yet he with God-like Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was willing to unite himſelf to our Nature, and to ſuffer Death for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners worthy of the deepeſt Laſhes; what Tenderneſs, what Love was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in that God who did in ſome ſort humble himſelf to ſave us? How pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is this Motive to affect generous Minds, and how difficult is it when we think ſeriouſly of the Benefits we have received from our Lord, how difficult is it, I ſay, to refuſe him a Heart to which his Title is ſo antecedently Juſt? Ah! if we are ſo ſenſible of the good Offices which are done us, where com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the Actors look aſquint on their own Intereſt, what Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ought we not to pay for ſo many Gratuitous Bounties as Jeſus Chriſt has conferr'd on us, only becauſe he lov'd us? This adorable Saviour has given us in his Life and Death a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Model of all the Virtues which
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:96673:102"/>can lead us up to that Immortal Crown he deſigns us, and he is deſirous, that we ſhould not deviate from his Steps; but yet ſurveying our Weakneſs, he has promis'd us a Reinforcement of his own Succours, with which we need not decline to combat thoſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable Enemies that have vow'd our Deſtruction. Let us charge then with Confidence under ſo great a Leader, we may well be undaunted under ſo good a Maſter, let us inviolably imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Brightneſs of his Example, and that our Wills may not be biaſs'd by the publick Obliquity of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, let us judge of things as he judg'd of 'em, let us pronounce that thoſe Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Pleaſures, and Honors which he deſpis'd, do not deſerve our conſtant Attendance on 'em; let us believe alſo, that the Sufferings, which he lov'd to that heighth as to die upon a Croſs, are leſs to be fear'd than wiſh'd for; and let us remember, that the way which he march'd to his Glory, that is now Triumphant, is not ſurcharg'd with the Gaiety of Flowers, but yet
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:96673:102"/>looks Graceful, tho 'twas dy'd with Blood, and water'd with Tears.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>LXXX.</hi> Of Death.</head>
               <p>AFter having propos'd my Thoughts about what we are to do, and what we are to avoid whilſt we wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this Lower Region; methinks 'tis pat to the purpoſe, to ſay ſomething of Death, which gives the finiſhing Stroke, and is the moſt important Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fleeting Life; I know very well, that the Separation of the Soul from the Body can be no Friendly Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and that the moſt reſolute Minds cannot behold it without ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſure that borders upon Fear; nevertheleſs, I do not think it is ſo hard a Task, as ſome fearful Souls who multiply their Terrours imagine 'tis, to bid the World adieu with the ſame Generoſity with which we liv'd in it; indeed why ſhould we dread the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:96673:103"/>thro' this Streight that has been open'd by other <hi>Columbus</hi>'s ſo many Ages ago? Is it not better with Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very to ſtand the Shock of that Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which we know before-hand is unavoidable, and from which not the ſubtleſt of all Mankind, by any eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Tricks can bolt; the Hope of Happineſs, which is aſſur'd to us, if we die with holy Diſpoſitions to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it, ought ſooner to quicken us to ſearch for Death, than to increaſe our Fear of loſing Life. If we are jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous that we ſhall be rack'd with ſome painful Agony, let us reflect that often 'tis light eno', or at leaſt, that 'tis quickly adjourn'd; and if the Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God's Judgments frights us, the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt ſhed for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and the infinite Love which he has for Souls that have coſt him ſo dear, ought to ſtill our Fears, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire us with much Confidence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement. If we are juſt (which yet a Man ought not to perſuade himſelf that he is) let us hope he will breath immortal Love on us, and crown thoſe
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:96673:103"/>Works which are the Reſults of his own Grace; and if we are Sinners, let us not deſpair of his Mercy, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that knows no Bounds, and that the Scripture tells us, that a broken and a contrite Heart he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe: The Grace of ſuch a happy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance which we ought to ask with Faith, Humility, and Perſeverance, is eno' to give us new Life after Death. Nevertheleſs, it muſt be own'd, that thoſe who neglecting the Obligations of their Religion, degrade themſelves by immerſing their Lives in ſenſual Fruitions, have reaſon to apprehend Death as a King of Terrours; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that their Ruine is certain, if they are catch'd unawares by it, which God knows, is too often, as we are aſſur'd by our Redeemer, put caſe a Diſtemper ſhould leave ſuch Men ſome Dregs of Time to think upon their Salvation, either they flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that it will not prove mortal, and ſo ſtop ſhort even in the Tendency to a Preparation for a dying hour, or if ſeeing themſelves at the laſt Gaſp,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:96673:104"/>they deſire to receive the Sacrament to huddle up a miſpent Life, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly 'tis more the Effect of a ſlaviſh Fear, than any Fruit of a true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, they do not ſincerely renounce the Pleaſures of the World, nor aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the Objects of their criminal Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which they have always doted on with ſo much vehemence; for that Love fortifi'd by long Cuſtom, has branch'd it ſelf in their Hearts with ſuch ſtubborn Roots, that it muſt be only a Miracle of Grace that can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce ſuch a cemented Acquaintance; and will God vouchſafe this extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Grace to thoſe who for ſo many years have impudently violated, and contemn'd his holy Laws? The ſureſt Means then to be arm'd againſt the Fears of Death, is for Gentlemen to prepare themſelves by a pure and innocent Life, timely to draw off from that which one day they muſt part withal for ever, to reflect of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that in that critical Moment where Eternity begins, the Pleaſures of Senſe expire; a Veil is drawn over all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:96673:104"/>Greatneſs, every gliſtering tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Advantage is vaniſh'd. Laſtly, they have no more to do but to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade themſelves convincingly, that there is no other Bottom to ſtay their Conſolation upon, but the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that they have lov'd God, and that they have ſerv'd him with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>variable Stedfaſtneſs, in ſpight of the over-bearing Corruption of a profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Age.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:105"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:105"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> AN Honeſt Man. <hi>Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Honoring of Parents. <hi>Page 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The Importance of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. <hi>Page 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> What a Young Gentleman ought to Learn. <hi>Page 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> What ought to be the Scope of his Studies. <hi>Page 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> To make a right Uſe of Knowledge. <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> What a Man is to do for his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Page 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> To be ſubject to the Laws of the Country. <hi>Page 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> The Duty of Allegiance is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Law. <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:106"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Againſt thoſe who dare cenſure the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>Page 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Againſt the Fomenters of Plots and Diſturbances. <hi>Page 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> The true Way to gain Eſteem. <hi>Page 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Of high Birth and Reputation. <hi>Page 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Of the Choice of a Station in the World. <hi>Page 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> To be Vigilant, Intent, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious. <hi>Page 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Of the Firſt Undertakings. <hi>Page 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Which is the beſt Way to gain the Eſteem of Princes and Great Men. <hi>Page 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> Of the Advantages of true Friendſhip. <hi>Page 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> Of the Choice of a Friend. <hi>Page 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> Of the Good and Ill Uſe of Time. <hi>Page 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> To ſpeak little, and hear others. <hi>Page 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Of Duels. <hi>Page 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXIII.</hi> To give Miniſters of State the Honors due to 'em. <hi>Page 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> Of the Love of Pleaſures. <hi>Page 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> To Study Himſelf. <hi>Page 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> To converſe with Wiſe Men of great Abilities. <hi>Page 73</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:106"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> To have Variety of Friends. <hi>Page 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Of Great Deſigns. <hi>Page 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> To Affect Nothing. <hi>Page 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> To know what will take with the Age. <hi>Page 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> To know how to be well employ'd when we are alone. <hi>Page 84.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> Not to judge of Actions by the Event. <hi>Page 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> What a Man is to do for his Friend. <hi>Page 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXIV.</hi> Of a Gay Humour, and the Uſe of Jeſting. <hi>Page 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> To neglect Nothing. <hi>Page 93</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Of the Uſe is to be made of Great Mens Favours. <hi>Page 94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Of Superfluity and Neatneſs. <hi>Page 97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> To have as few Enemies as you can. <hi>Page 98</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Not to be Diſcourag'd. <hi>Page 100</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> Of Pride. <hi>Page 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> To Regulate a Man's Expences. <hi>Page 104</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:107"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> To know how to chuſe his Company. <hi>Page 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> Of ſharp Raillery and Villifying. <hi>Page 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLIV.</hi> Of Sincerity. <hi>Page 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> Of Reconciliations. <hi>Page 112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> Not to be Fickle. <hi>Page 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> The Character af a Cowardly and Faint-hearted Man. <hi>Page 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLVIII.</hi> Of Gratitude. <hi>Page 119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> To avoid Conteſts. <hi>Page 121</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>L.</hi> To be Regular in his Conduct. <hi>Page 124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LI.</hi> How one may make a Judgment of Men. <hi>Page 125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> Of the Management of Proſperity and Adverſity. <hi>Page 128</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LIII.</hi> Of Credential Letters, ſigning Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers with Blanks. <hi>Page 130</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LIV.</hi> Of Curioſity. <hi>Page 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LV.</hi> To ſhun the Converſation of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines and Cowards. <hi>Page 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LVI.</hi> Not to uſe Reſerves, but in Caſes of Neceſſity. <hi>Page 138</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LVII.</hi> Of the Death of a Friend. <hi>Page 139</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:107"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>LVIII.</hi> At the Court Diffidence is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>Page 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LIX.</hi> Of Paſſions in thoſe who are well in Years. <hi>Page 143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LX.</hi> Of Counſel <hi>Page 144</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXI.</hi> The Duties of Perſons advanc'd to a high Poſt. <hi>Page 145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXII.</hi> Not to give haſty Anſwers in Weighty Matters. <hi>Page 148</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXIII.</hi> Not to protect the Wicked. <hi>Page 149</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXIV.</hi> How a Man is to carry himſelf towards the Ungrateful. <hi>Page 150</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXV.</hi> What muſt be obſerv'd in great Undertakings. <hi>Page 152</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXVI.</hi> Of a Secret. <hi>Page 154</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXVII.</hi> Of Hope and Deſpair <hi>Page 158</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXVIII.</hi> To take Virtues Part. <hi>Page 161</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXIX.</hi> Of Irreſolution. <hi>Page 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXX.</hi> Not to be raſh in Judging. <hi>Page 164</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXI.</hi> How we ought to treat them who have been any way aſſiſtant to us. <hi>Page 167</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXII.</hi> Of unforeſeen Accidents. <hi>Page 168</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXIII.</hi> Of Favours, of Reconciliations, and of the Diſpoſal of Offices. <hi>Page 170</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:96673:108"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXIV.</hi> Of the Way to Grant or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe Kindneſſes. <hi>Page 172</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXV.</hi> Of a Retir'd, and a Court-Life. <hi>Page 174</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXVI.</hi> What Sentiments the Uſe of the Creatures ſhould inſpire us with. <hi>Page 177</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXVII.</hi> Of Baniſhment. <hi>Page 179</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXVIII.</hi> Of Impriſonment. <hi>Page 181</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXIX.</hi> Of the Love and Imitation of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Page 184</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LXXX.</hi> Of Death. <hi>Page 187</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:96673:108"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 3. Line 23. read on. Pag. 6. lin. 10. for withit read with it. p. 12. at the top, for II. r. III. p. 29. l. 16. f. I that r. that I. p. 109. l. 6. put a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma at beſides, inſtead of at diſcreet. p. 114. l. 18. a Colon inſtead of the Interrogation Point. p. 121. l. 4. put the Comma after it, and not at ſhun. p. 125. l. 5. a point of Interrogation is to be put inſtead of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon. p, 128. l. 4. put it before eaſily, p. 134. l. 10. put a Comma after happen, p. 141. l. 13. f. ſuch r. ſuch. p. 131. l. ult. a point of Interrogation, p. 175. l. 24. place a point of Interrogation. p. 177. l. 5. a Semi-Colon inſtead of an Interrogation, p. 163. l. 16. for exſtinguiſh r. extinguiſh. for Carier read Career.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
